In India, truck drivers navigate
treacherous roads to deliver critical
supplies. And in the US, workers provide
meals, haircuts, and even dental care at
the largest truck stop in the country.
We've traveled the globe to learn about
the world's most [music] fascinating
jobs.
We'll start with the people making food
consumed miles above the earth's
surface.
Airplane food has a bad reputation, but
the Qatar Airways cooks are whipping up
high-quality food every day.
>> Every single dish is made from scratch
at the Qatar Airways catering kitchen in
Doha.
It turns out more than 200,000 fresh
meals a day, even for regional
short-haul flights.
It all needs to be prepared about 48
hours before takeoff.
>> I think perhaps the biggest challenge is
just ensuring that there's consistency
and that everything runs smoothly.
>> The chefs here believe it's part of the
reason the airline has been named number
one in the [music] world for the eighth
time since 2011.
This kind of cooking used to be the
standard in most flights in America,
too, no matter what cabin you flew on.
But today,
most US airlines don't [music] run their
own kitchens, opting to buy from
catering services instead.
So, why has economy airplane food gone
from luxury to a point of ridicule
[music] in the US?
And why do so few airlines still cook
their own meals?
No workers are allowed to step foot in
the kitchen without walking through this
air shower corridor first.
>> To ensure that we have no biological or
any physical contaminants go into the
kitchen.
>> This is Filipe Hempis playground.
4,000 people from 38 countries at the
Qatar Aircraft Catering Company, or
QACC.
It's a part of the Qatar Airways Group.
The team develops new menus every 3
months.
All the produce is fresh.
Even though they're operating in a food
desert.
They go through 30 metric tons of fruits
and vegetables daily and use custom
machines to help prep them for meals.
Like this bin that can wash 12,000
peppers a day.
And this machine that peels six
cantaloupes in under a minute.
Other produce like dragon fruit,
strawberries, white asparagus,
get a more delicate treatment. They're
peeled and carved by hand.
>> It's a big routine making almost 200,000
meals a day. The team is rotated
throughout their time working here.
>> Inside the hot kitchen, the aroma of
cumin, garlic, and onions fills the air.
Chefs prepare dishes of several
different cuisines from Indian to Arabic
and Asian.
>> We base them mostly on the demographics
of that flight.
For example, for America, we have a lot
of traffic from the Indian subcontinent.
>> They use over 300 potatoes every day
[music] to make aloo tikki, a popular
street food in India.
The kitchen goes through 36,000
whole fresh eggs a week.
And another 3 and 1/2 tons of
pasteurized egg whites are turned into
12,000 omelets a day.
Even the smallest change can be costly.
>> We need to ensure that we're going to
able to meet the quantities without
having to make any substitutions. The
moment we have any substitutions, then
menu cards will be affected and and
things like that.
>> There's also a big emphasis on making
most food from scratch.
Even for items that are often bought
frozen or pre-made.
Like sausages
and pasta.
>> If you're ordering ravioli from economy
class, you're getting freshly made
pasta, which not many airlines do that.
>> Bread products are also prepared on
site.
Bakers turn out 10,000 croissants an
hour.
As well as handmade focaccias.
Pastry chefs design new desserts every
quarter.
Like these chocolate brownies made from
scratch.
>> We're giving this in economy and it's a
homemade eggless brownie. Tastes really
good with a mousse underneath.
>> While people here handle food all day
long,
taste testing is only reserved for a
select few.
>> For each of our kitchens, we have a
centralized tasting area.
So I'm here with Chef Harish, who's our
executive chef for QACC.
Our senior chefs will taste the food,
log it down, and give their comments. If
something does not pass our criteria, we
redo the meals.
>> Pretty good?
>> Yeah? You agree?
>> Qatar Airways has a total of 270
international flights leaving from Doha
per day. And on average, the airline
serves 350 meals on each flight.
This facility also provides meals to
other Oneworld Alliance partners that
fly out of Doha.
And to the 19 lounges
>> [music]
>> at Hamad International Airport.
All the food is halal.
Prepared in accordance with Islamic
dietary laws because Qatar is a Muslim
country.
So for example, you won't find any pork
on the menu.
But when it comes to drinks, the airline
does serve alcohol once you're up in the
clouds.
Unlike some Muslim carriers like Saudia
or Kuwait Airways, where it's banned.
Once each dish is finalized, it's
stacked on a tray and labeled.
>> The reason we put a barcode is to ensure
we have traceability for every dish
as well as for the team on the other
side to be able to easily find what they
need for assembly.
>> It also helps them track any food safety
issues down the line.
>> We can trace it all the way back to the
person that made it, the day they made
it, the time they made it, [music] and
we can then further investigate if
there's a need.
>> The trays are cooled for 90 minutes to
prevent the growth of any bacteria or
pathogens. And then,
>> temperature is checked once again by
infrared thermometer,
and the food is covered,
scanned,
and sent for storage.
>> It's not possible for the airline to
prepare everything on the day of the
flight. So usually, they make food in
advance and refrigerate it for 1 day at
the most. [music]
Any longer and the taste and texture
could change, especially for starchy
foods like rice or pasta.
But nothing is fully frozen.
This cooling chamber is set to below 5°
C
and can store 3,500 trays at a time.
A robotic arm adds and removes trays as
needed across 30 levels.
In the cold kitchen, workers prepare
fruit bowls, dips,
and about 12,000 sandwiches a day.
Many of these items end up on short-haul
flights, which are less than 3 hours
long.
>> Peter here will request our mashed
potatoes.
>> A few hours before the flight takes off,
the food trays that were stored in the
chiller are brought back in for
portioning.
Workers on this line have their eyes at
all times on the golden sample.
The combos are endless and change
depending on the route.
The economy meals are dished up on trays
and packed away.
Business class meals are temporarily
portioned in these foil containers.
Flight attendants will later plate and
serve these dishes paying a lot of
attention to the presentation, which
will ultimately look like this.
Qatar Airways tries to bring hints of
luxury to economy too in the details.
They offer 18 meals that customers with
special dietary needs can pre-order.
>> We have sort of our religious meals. We
also have our medical meals and then we
have our specific meals like child
meals, [music] etc.
>> The culinary team has designed 50 meal
choices for economy [music] and first
class each and 150 for business class
that are dished out based on a flight's
route and duration.
Every cabin gets real silverware.
All these items are dried, hand
polished, and assembled again ready for
the next flight.
>> We're always looking at ways of to
reduce single-use plastic.
We are looking at materials for a meal
[music] kits to be able to to have less
impact on the environment.
>> Qatar Airways won several awards
including the Apex award for best food
and beverage.
But they can't maintain high standards
by only sourcing local products.
As Qatar is one of the hottest and
driest countries in the world
with no lakes or rivers.
Growing things here is hard.
>> Currently, we have more imported
ingredients than than local.
However, this is something that we're
trying to change.
We're working together with a lot of
local farms, fisheries to to provide
some of our products.
>> That includes tomatoes, cucumbers,
spinach, and bok choy.
The trays are stacked on these carts
that are rolled onto trucks that head
for the tarmac.
The trolleys are pushed onto the
aircraft and [music] locked into the
galleys.
Flight attendants then work their magic.
>> We have newer generation ovens, which
allow individualization of temperature
and humidity when it comes to reheating
the meals.
>> Truck drivers in India provide an
essential service to villagers in the
Himalayas.
>> [music]
>> They transport food, water, and medicine
to remote regions, but the crucial work
comes [music] at a deadly cost.
Killar road, deep in the Himalayas,
is one of the most dangerous in the
world.
One reckless turn could send drivers
hurtling down nearly 11,000 ft.
Still, every summer Ankur Rawat makes
several trips,
delivering basic supplies to remote
villages along this perilous route.
It connects the rest of India to the
isolated region of Pangi Valley,
which is cut off for nearly 6 months of
the year because of heavy snow.
But sometimes trucks break down along
the way, leaving drivers stranded for
days.
So, what does it take to navigate these
heavy-duty trucks on this deadly path?
We rode along with Anku through the
mountains for 3 days to find out.
Anku lives in the village of Palhoon
with his wife Savita and their children.
He never really knows what the weather
will be.
So, he packs plenty of blankets.
They sit down for a family dinner
before Anku sets off.
He first picks up the truck from a
private parking lot that rents them out.
This one has a power steering and a 5600
cc engine, ideal for driving through the
mountains.
Anku will make a few pit stops on this
107-mi journey.
First, [music] he'll travel about 10 mi
from his home to a warehouse in Chamba
to pick up food rations.
Then, he'll pass through several small
towns and go through Sach Pass, the
highest point on Killar Road, before
reaching his destination, the district
of Pangi Valley.
Today, Anku's loading 100-lb bags of
wheat
provided by the government to sustain
[music] India's most isolated regions.
His truck can carry up to 12 tons.
But any more than that, [music] and it
could topple over.
He always stops at this local temple
along the way.
The truck can hold up to 250 L of
diesel.
But there are hardly any gas stations
along the route.
The terrain starts off pretty smooth.
But as the truck goes uphill,
it gets rough.
And his speed drops below 10 [music]
mph.
At this point, the road is only 10 ft
wide.
And there's barely room for two cars to
drive next to each other.
So when another vehicle approaches,
Uncle needs to carefully reverse,
sometimes by hundreds of yards.
Luckily, he's traveling with truck
conductor Muhammad Nisar Mughal,
who jumps out and guides Uncle around
blind spots and dangerous turns.
>> There are no guardrails to prevent them
from veering off.
In July 2022, a Jeep rolled into a gorge
killing five people. And in 2023, seven
people died after their vehicle was hit
by a landslide on this route.
But after years of experience as a
trucker, Anku isn't easily intimidated.
All the traditional rules of the road
don't really apply.
Truck drivers communicate with hand
signals, [music]
which becomes important during moments
of congestion like this.
They also use pressure horns,
which are illegal in India. But Anku
says they need them for safety reasons.
Anku doesn't wear a seatbelt, either,
even though under Indian law he's
required to.
He says for this type of driving, they
can do more harm than good, as they
restrict the driver from leaning over.
But stats on semi-truck accidents show
that drivers are more likely to survive
if they buckle up.
In this state alone, trucks and buses
accounted for 12% of all fatal crashes
[music] in 2022.
Landslides and snowfall have also
weakened this road structure, forming
dishes and piles of debris.
So, the government hires contractors to
keep repairing it.
Killar Road [music] started off as a
footpath with narrow trails carved by
shepherds and traders who were trying to
reach the remote Pangi Valley.
Legend has it that residents of Chamba
fled to the hidden region to escape
Mughal invaders.
Others believe that in the 16th century,
the king of Chamba banished criminals to
this isolated region.
These days, Killar Road is used mainly
by tourists, bikers seeking an
adrenaline rush, truckers, and local
residents.
After about 8 to 9 hours of driving,
the men pull over.
They make a fire to start cooking with
groceries they brought from home.
But even during dinner, they stay
vigilant in case they're confronted by
wild animals or thieves.
There are no hotels for miles, so they
sleep in the truck's [music] cabin.
The next day, they start driving at the
crack of dawn.
Killar Road gets even treacherous and
spectacular as trucks pass through
waterfalls
and incredibly tight spaces.
>> [music]
>> Vehicles along this route often run into
mechanical problems.
This truck carrying grains to Pangi
Valley broke down after the gearbox
stopped working.
The mechanic says the nearest store for
car parts is about 180 miles away.
The whole process will take four days
and the truck will just stay here until
then.
Anku and his team
carry on with their journey.
At around midday, they stop at a local
dhaba for a quick bite.
These cafes cater to truck drivers.
The people who run them, like Lakshman
Sharma, understand how hard it is to
drive around here.
But even these cafes close down once it
starts snowing around October.
While Anku's job is an essential
service, he only makes about 10,000
rupees a month.
That's about 4 US dollars a day.
Enough to buy a few pounds of rice and
lentils in India.
>> [music]
>> He could make about 25,000 rupees a
month as a personal driver in Delhi or
Bombay.
But his heart belongs here in the
Himalayas.
And he wants the whole world to know how
beautiful these mountains are.
So he vlogs on the side.
He has about 50,000 followers and
counting on YouTube.
But the most treacherous part of this
route is getting through Sach Pass.
At nearly 14,500 feet,
Sach Pass is one of the highest
navigable places in the state of
Himachal Pradesh.
Drivers are advised [music] not to stop
at the top for more than 5 minutes
because there's so little oxygen in the
air.
The road through here is even more
narrow.
Barely more than 8 feet wide.
So uncle needs to be extremely mindful
when navigating the steep slope.
>> It takes him about 3 to 4 hours to go
through this 9-mi stretch.
After they're through, Anku recaps the
journey for his followers.
Killar is among 106 villages in Pangi
Valley, which has a total population of
just 18,000 people.
Almost 200 trucks head there every
summer, carrying food, medicine, and
other basic supplies.
They store it in this warehouse for the
winter, and residents buy them at a
subsidized rate set by the government.
As soon as they're done unloading, Anku
and his colleagues hit the road.
Along the way, they pass by a nomadic
community called the Gujjars.
For Uncle, catching up with them over a
cup of tea has become a ritual.
Even though driving through these
mountains is a part of Uncle's identity,
the job has worn him down.
But he still yearns for the day he can
truly enjoy the breathtaking nature
around him.
>> After training to become a Navy culinary
specialist,
seamen can be placed as cooks on a
submarine,
an environment with a unique set of
challenges.
>> These Navy culinary specialists
are preparing 15 lb of turkey, 10 lb of
ham,
and pulled pork sandwiches made from
scratch, along with mac and cheese,
corn, mashed potatoes, and cookies
to serve a crew of 150 sailors.
>> Pulled pork,
macaroni.
>> And they only have about 5 hours to
prepare each meal.
>> You want the soup, too?
>> But this isn't your typical Navy galley.
This is where meals are made
on a submarine
in classified locations deep at sea. The
crew of the nuclear-powered USS South
Dakota works around the clock to monitor
>> Emergency bearing my depth 155 ft pilot
eye.
>> and potentially engage with foreign
threats.
>> We're tasked to go do something
and we go do it.
>> For up to 9 months, they work and live
within the tight confines of their
windowless ship where every role is
critical to the mission success.
Among them are the culinary specialists.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> These crew members have an essential
responsibility,
feeding up to 150 sailors and fueling
them for the challenges that lie ahead.
>> We are essentially the morale of the
fleet. Like if our morale is low, their
morale's going to be low and you can
easily taste it in the food.
>> Business Insider spent 2 days aboard the
USS South Dakota while it lay in port at
Naval Submarine Base New London in
Groton, Connecticut
observing culinary specialists preparing
breakfast, lunch, and dinner for the
crew.
>> The USS South Dakota is a Virginia class
submarine. Specifically, it's a block
three, meaning it has a few more
capabilities and a few more
modifications than the regular Virginia
class submarines. And the the ship is
manned 24 hours a day, 7 days a week
while we're in port uh for security
reasons.
>> While some off-duty crew members go home
to see their families,
those on board rely on the meals
prepared by the culinary specialists.
>> It might not be everyone all at once,
but I'm going to feed everyone. So, if I
have 150 people on board, I'm going to
feed 150 people pretty much almost every
meal.
>> Because the USS South Dakota is a
nuclear powered submarine, its time at
sea is limited only by the amount of
food it can carry.
>> About 2 weeks in, you'll probably run
out of fresh food. That's the
unfortunate reality of it. So, we have
some food in the outboards. We have food
in every locker imaginable. If there's
space available and we can kind of
quickly put food up there and maybe
ratchet down. We'll take that
opportunity to do that.
>> Fully stocked, the sub carries about 90
days worth of food.
>> The strategy for keeping fresh food
aboard a submarine is you just accept
when you run out of fresh food. And the
second you get an opportunity to get
more fresh food on, you take that
opportunity.
Today for dinner we're having
Thanksgiving. So we're having turkey,
ham, mashed potatoes, gravy, hot rolls
for our bread.
So this right here is essentially my
menu. Uh the actual name for it is the
food preparation worksheet. But layman's
terms, this is essentially my menu. This
uh tells me everything that I'm having
for breakfast, lunch, and dinner.
>> Today, Petty Officer CSS Wesley Whitson
is preparing 10 lb of ham and 15 lb of
turkey.
>> So the turkey itself I'm going to have
to actually like cut up a little bit,
you know, throw some seasoning on. But
the ham I literally just
unwrap it, throw it in a pan, wrap it
up, call it a day.
That Yeah, that I can do real quick. Uh
so yeah, let's get with that.
And then when I'm ready, I'm just going
to throw it in the oven and then I'm
just going to let it make out.
Really easy, nothing
nothing too crazy.
And done. Yay, one less thing I got to
worry about.
Okay.
Manning for us is supposed to be roughly
about like seven or eight.
I don't have that right now, so
I'm I'm working with what I got. But
because there's only so few of us, not
only are you know, we essentially you
know, manager, but I'm also the cook. I
am the guy that has to make it. So I not
only have to manage everything, but I
have to make sure that I'm actually
getting it done myself. Days will
usually take care of like lunch and
dinner and
you know, for the meals. Uh the night
guy will kind of help prep for lunch a
little bit, but the day guys will will
take over and they'll finish it.
>> With extended [music] deployments,
confined spaces, and shifts that can
last up to 12 hours, submarine
assignments aren't desirable to many.
>> Not a lot of people want to, you know,
wanted to join the military, but also
not a lot of people wanting to join
subs, you know, within the Navy,
uh especially as a culinary specialist
as a cook.
And I I get it. This job isn't for
everyone.
>> To compensate, the Navy offers an
additional $85 to $600 a month to
submarine crew members based on rank and
time in service.
Culinary specialists who work aboard
submarines earn a base salary of about
$26,000.
>> Now, I just let those sit and proof.
So, I'll give them roughly about an hour
or so, and then
I'll turn it over to actually bake, and
then they should be good to go.
So, not only am I the galley watch
captain, uh but I am also uh our bulk
store custodian or JOD as we call it,
which stands for jack of the dust. That
responsibility for me is to go about and
uh do what we call breakouts uh or
shopping
uh to put it in layman's terms. They'll
look at the menu, they'll write a list
of like what groceries, you know, what
food items they need or groceries, and
they'll be like, "I need this stuff."
And I'll take it be like, "All right."
And then I just go to where we keep all
of our food, you know, all the
storerooms on board, uh and then I will
break it out uh for them. That way they
have it available for the next day.
>> Food is kept in storerooms, small
cabinets, and other locations around the
ship. But because of operational
security concerns, cameras were only
allowed in the galley during our visit.
>> Space is a luxury on a submarine, so
definitely keeping food anywhere we can
to maximize the amount that we have on
board. So,
actually in all of these uh
bench seats will have food, as well as
these backs will have
some extra dry provisions.
And that'll be the same for all these
bench seats that will have
some uh maple syrup, chocolate syrup,
strawberry syrup. So, any kind of
random select items like that. We'll
have soy sauce in those. We'll have
seasoning in these outboard ones.
Yeah, so we got bags of soup in there.
So, I am the supply officer chop on
board. Uh what that means I'm
responsible for both the food service
division and the logistics division. So,
the first storm I have is the forward
storm or the can room, which as the name
implies is just full of cans. Typically,
this room is actually a lot more full
with cans coming all the way up to this
front door and then actually going to
the ceiling. So, as we fill this up with
more cans, kind of like deciding what
we're going to use first and making sure
those are actually put in the front.
When the guys need to get something out
of the freezer, they'll actually uh put
a jacket on, get a headlamp on, get a
beanie on. Pretty much just layer up
like they're going to go in a cold area
like this area is below freezing most
time. Right now, it's -3.9°.
>> All food aboard submarines is logged and
tracked every day. And the budget for
meals is determined by a daily allowance
per sailor.
>> If we're in port, we can spend anywhere
from like $700 to $1,000 a day. And then
if we're out to sea, anywhere from about
$1,600 to like $2,800 per day. We
operate off of a 28-day cycle menu.
We'll have the same meals every 28 days.
It's definitely designed where it
creates that kind of consistency
throughout the week. So, if you're
having Italian on a night, you know it's
a Thursday. Or if you're having pizza
for dinner, then you know it's a
Saturday. So, it helps the crew kind of
keep their own pace and honestly helps
them pass the time. If you're like, "Oh
wow, this is the second time we've had
pizza this underway." then you know it's
already been 2 weeks.
>> Ooh, I can smell it.
Ooh, almost. Almost.
>> Back in the kitchen,
culinary specialist Whitson has just 1
hour
before the crew begins to line up for
dinner.
>> Ooh.
How's it feel to be done cooking?
>> Feels good.
Good to know that
all I have left is to serve this out.
And then after that it's just clean up
and then I'm done.
I got a whole lot of going on.
I'm going home to my wife
and I'm getting my cuddles.
>> [laughter]
>> I appreciate all you guys. I will take
everything but the ham.
>> Extra ham?
>> I got you.
>> Extra ham? I got you. Just Just for you
cuz I know how much you love that pork.
>> Oh man, you already know.
>> No corn and no soup. Extra corn, extra
soup?
I got you.
>> It's great. It's great.
>> I remember three years
>> I honestly love cooking. I love being in
the galley. I love working with food. I
love putting out really good meals and
making people happy with them. I You
know, I like seeing everyone being
fulfilled and having a good meal and
enjoying themselves with it.
>> On a sub, there is no internet, cell
service, or access to the outside world
other than mission-critical
communications and the occasional email
from family transmitted via secure
satellite leaving crew members to find
their own ways of staying entertained
during the little downtime they get.
>> I'm either reading a book, watching TV,
whether be like a TV show or a movie, or
I'm playing on my laptop.
>> My favorite way to pass time underway
was honestly just spending time with my
guys. You know, maybe if it's just
playing chess and cruise master like
even just listening to music in my room
or listening to music in the wardroom.
Just That's
distracting yourself in a way but also
keeping yourself busy while keeping your
mind active. I think that's the best way
to do it.
>> On every submarine, the crew's mess
[music] is designed to reflect a piece
of the state it's named after.
Aboard the USS [music] South Dakota, the
space draws inspiration from Deadwood's
iconic saloon number 10.
>> That's where the crew goes to relax.
It's also where they eat. That's also
where they,
>> [music]
>> you know, kind of let their hair down
and study if they if they need to or
play cards, play dominoes, play video
games, conduct training. It's kind of
all all-purpose, and that's what the did
with saloon was to South Dakota back
[music] in the 1800s.
>> The next day, culinary specialist Lupon
Jimenez steps into the galley ready to
prepare breakfast for the crew.
On the menu this morning,
steak and egg burritos,
pancakes, hash browns, and bacon.
It takes 3 hours to prepare the meal.
>> May I do a steak burrito with eggs and
bacon?
>> And at 7:00, the hungry sailors make
their way to the crew's mess for
breakfast.
As breakfast comes to an end,
>> When you getting that pork butt going?
>> Uh
in a couple minutes.
>> Are you guys starting lunch already?
>> Yeah.
>> There's barely a moment to rest. Jimenez
[music] must quickly shift gears and
start preparing lunch to make sure he
can feed 150 crew members.
>> Time is like pretty irrelevant here on
the sub cuz we're just working by hours.
It's 12 hours on, 12 hours off. And then
once we get off,
>> [music]
>> it's either
go have fun or go straight to the
straight to bed.
This is about to be the pulled pork. I'm
putting the meat into the mixer along
with the juices. It was boiling to shred
the pork rather than me taking a [music]
long time by hand. The quicker you get
it done, the less you got to worry
about. But you still got a time
management to the meal hour, that way it
doesn't just sit on the line for a very
long time because that becomes a bad
thing.
>> Meal today is the house pulled pork,
pulled pork mac and cheese and corn
chowder. It's actually one of my
favorite things to make. Out of all of
them,
uh the mac cheese is probably my
favorite thing to make.
>> I'm going to have to go to Milly with
his mac and cheese. Sometime he would
like make his favorite, which is spicy
mac and cheese. Really spicy for some
reason. I feel like he puts like ghost
pepper hot sauce in there or something.
But, uh, I don't know. It's good.
I'm about to make some hot roll dough
and turn them into like buns from
scratch.
>> How many rolls do you have to make?
>> I'm going to get at least around 100 and
120.
>> How many do you have so far?
>> Woo, I'll say about probably 80.
120 were last made throughout the meal
and then it showed me that I have at
least a little bit left over.
That's what I'm going for, that way I
don't run out.
>> Is it a little more salt?
Do you have a potato in
>> No, we don't have potato.
>> Will it be hot?
>> Uh,
I don't
>> Nice.
>> Please don't put a lot in there.
>> No, I won't.
I like that deep one outside of this.
That's definitely on the front side.
Yeah, can you get like a little more
salt? That should be good.
>> As the lunch hour nears,
the ward room is prepared.
A space designated for the ship's
officers.
>> There's significantly less officers on
board a submarine than there are
enlisted. Uh, so they get their own
room.
>> For lunch today we have pulled pork, mac
and cheese, cauliflower, and green
beans.
>> Very good, thank you.
>> Typically used for work, relaxation, and
socializing, the ward room becomes a
dining room during mealtimes.
>> For the officers, [music] this is their
place to come and eat. The family style
meal serving that happens in the
wardroom is very history rich.
>> While the dinner service is a [music]
privilege for the officers aboard,
it's not uncommon for them to join the
crew in the crew's mess.
>> Boat board.
Macaroni.
>> Mhm.
>> I like when you put them together.
>> Mhm. Got to.
>> That was boat day.
>> Mac and cheese is always the bomb. I
love boat board.
>> I like the mac and cheese, the boat
board, and
>> Before returning to sea, the USS South
Dakota will undergo thorough
maintenance, followed by sea
certification, a process that tests both
the crew and the submarine to ensure all
systems are fully operational for the
next deployment.
>> It is exhausting, it is tiresome, and it
wears on you real quick if you let it.
But knowing that I'm able to feed people
and that they are happy with what I put
out, and they look forward to what I can
bring to the table, that that makes that
makes it worth it for me.
>> Reaching Everest peak is an adventurer's
holy grail, but most can't do it without
the help of experienced Sherpa guides.
It's a dangerous profession on the verge
of disappearing.
A small shift of this ladder can turn
catastrophic in a matter of seconds.
Navigating this path safely is the
responsibility of Everest climbing
guides, many of whom are ethnic Sherpas
who earn $4 to $10,000
per climb.
But usually, these guides can count on
only one expedition per year.
The job is one of the most dangerous in
the world.
>> I would say my daughter and your your
your
And while 2023 saw the most climbers on
record, it also saw [music] the most
deaths.
332 people have been lost to Everest in
the last [music] century. Over a third
of them were mountain guides.
It's 2:00 a.m. at base camp, and Furba
Wangchu Sherpa is leading a team of
guides and climbers up the world's
tallest mountain.
>> [music]
>> Furba Wangchu has touched Everest's peak
14 times already.
>> [panting]
>> He begins every climb with a puja
ceremony, praying for safe passage and
paying respect to the mountain.
Even with his success rate, he never
underestimates the deadly risks. [music]
Over the next several weeks, this group
of 16 will climb for hours on end in
total darkness, face the threat of
avalanches and storms, and cross deadly
passageways.
Purba Wangchu and his team of
experienced guides are their best
[music] chance of making it to the
summit and surviving.
>> It gives you a lot of confidence.
You know, when your Sherpa has 15, 16
summits, like some [music] of these
Sherpas here,
when you're at high altitude and you're
in those situations, and they tell you,
you know, it's okay, it's going to be
okay, it's very reassuring that they've
summited so many times.
>> It's more than just mentally reassuring.
On the mountain, the choices guides make
directly affect whether a climber lives.
The next morning, another group of
climbers is gearing up for its
expedition.
>> It takes a bit of time not to put it,
but it's safety of foot on the minus 30
or 50 sometimes.
>> Near base camp at 5,364
m, climbing guides lead a vital training
course.
Without this refresher, climbers won't
know how to work with their specific
expedition team.
The guides are using the limited time
they have today to review how best to
handle steep inclines and to teach this
team how to problem-solve on the spot.
>> Sorry.
>> Yeah.
>> The course is one of the services
included in a mountain guide's cost.
Guides only work with experienced
[music] high-altitude mountaineers, a
requirement of the Nepalese government.
But that doesn't mean the climbers are
ready to brave Everest's extreme climate
yet.
>> I think if you are talking about
high-altitude mountaineering, it's
important to do
this, you know, at least every 6 months.
It keeps your body
ready for, I think, lack [music] of
oxygen.
I came here by helicopter, which is not
probably it was not the best idea. So,
the first stage was quite hard.
>> It'll be Ismail's second attempt at
summiting Everest.
He confronted the danger that awaits his
new team over a decade ago.
>> We almost reached 8,500, but because of
the very unfavorable
weather conditions, had to return.
So, the summit was very close. So, after
11 years, I'm back.
>> Ismail averted catastrophe in his first
[music] summit attempt, but not everyone
is so lucky.
When climbers are critically injured,
guides have to be prepared to switch an
expedition to a rescue and provide
emergency relief.
In May 2023, a team of Sherpa guides
[music]
rescued a climber from Everest's death
zone.
Over the course [music] of 6 hours, the
guides carried him on their backs down
to camp three.
Since the [music] 2019 season, as a
safety measure, Nepal has required every
climber to be accompanied by at least
one climbing guide.
And choosing a local guide has its
distinct benefits on Everest.
Many of these mountain guides are
Sherpas, an ethnic group natives to the
slopes of Mount Everest.
>> The conquering team was composed of 20
Americans
>> [music]
>> aided by Sherpa tribesmen who acted as
carriers.
>> Though the term Sherpa is informally
used as a catchall for Everest guides,
the Sherpa people have been closely
involved in mountaineering here since
the very first Everest expeditions.
Their tissues use oxygen more
efficiently and preserve muscle energy
better [music] than people from
lowlands.
That's one of the reasons Sherpa guides
can assist their climbers with heavy
loads without risking as much physical
strain.
>> I've got a very good Sherpa, um, you
know, and he carries he carries, um, a
lot.
So, about 10 kg I would carry, but they
would carry three times that.
>> And it's indispensable, especially here
at the Khumbu Icefall,
where three Sherpas lost their lives in
2023.
At an elevation of 5,486
m, the team slowly makes its way through
shifting glaciers.
>> The group is also relying on the work
that locals known as icefall doctors did
months earlier.
These specialized climbers establish the
safest route to the top of Everest every
season.
A separate fee of $600 per expedition
member goes to these icefall doctors to
use the ladders and ropes they set up.
But even with a clear path, climbers are
still in danger of crevasses opening and
closing and even unexpected avalanches.
>> [music]
>> Considering the danger, it's no surprise
that mountain guides are one of the
biggest expenses in summiting Everest.
Climbers pay as much as $100,000
for the expedition and a chance at
standing at the top of the world.
For each of these climbs, guides
certified by the International
Federation of Mountain Guides
Associations can charge agencies
$10,000.
Less experienced climbing guides make
only $4,000 per climb.
The agency Furba Wangchu works with,
Makalu Adventure, says it pays guides an
additional $1,500
for every successful summit.
>> I think it's okay for for what it is.
Um it's okay and you know, the Nepalese
government have to make money from it.
The sherpas have to have to make money
and you know, it would be an [music]
insult, I think, if we we just come and
and pay hardly anything and and summit
the mountain.
>> The majority of summits occur in the
spring season. So, most [music] guides
are hired for only one expedition,
limiting their yearly income.
Furba Wangchu says guides don't see
enough money to justify continuously
risking their lives.
>> The Himalayan terrain is so steep
though. The person that I'm going to
climb up is so
above above the lower part of the
journey is so I'm going to buy but I'm
going to go above just go above the
river but I'm going to go above the
river. Above [music] the lower part of
the journey is so I'm going to buy but
I'm going above the lower part of the
journey is so I'm going to buy but I'm
going to go above the
>> Guides also have to pay [music] for
their own gear, an investment of as much
as $7,000.
That includes clothing, boots, and
backpacks that must withstand extreme
conditions on the mountain.
The down suit alone can cost $2,000
and some gear needs to be replaced every
few years.
Often times, working as a guide in the
increasingly commercialized Everest
industry [music] comes out of necessity.
>> Above the mountain terrain is so above
the lower part of the journey is so I'm
going [music] to buy but above the lower
part of the journey is so I'm going to
above the lower part of the journey is
so I'm going to buy but I'm going to go
above the river.
Above the lower part of the journey is
so I'm going to
above the lower
above the lower part of the journey is
so I'm going to buy but I'm going
so I'm going to buy but I'm going to go
above the river but I'm going to go
above the river but I'm going
>> Despite of flood, Furba Wangchu takes on
other work.
This is common for [music] many local
guides who struggle to make ends meet
from a job that routinely puts their
life in danger.
>> [music]
>> That's one of the reasons Dawa Geljen
Sherpa quit his career as a climbing
guide.
Like Dawa Geljen, Furba Wangchu openly
questions whether the risks are really
worth it. And he thinks it's a question
more Sherpa guides will ask.
If Furba Wangchu is right, a declining
number of expert mountain guides will
coincide with the growing Everest
tourism industry.
In spring 2023, Nepal issued a record
number of 478
permits to summit Mount Everest.
This broke the record set 2 years
earlier when it issued 409 permits.
But as the industry grows, so too
[music] does the frequency of
fatalities.
Spring 2023 saw 18 deaths, 15 confirmed
and three presumed, making it the
deadliest season for climbers on
Everest.
Six of those lost were Sherpa guides.
At the same time, Nepal is seeing a
growing job market with locals
increasingly choosing other professions.
>> [music]
>> The rising death toll on Everest has put
more pressure on the Nepalese government
to manage tourism on the mountain.
In 2025, it plans to increase the price
of climbing permits for foreigners to
$15,000,
up from $11,000.
The government says the salaries of
high-altitude guides and workers will
also increase.
This could be a beacon of hope for some
younger locals who still see a future in
being a mountain guide, like Shashank
and Tsering Rai.
>> Climber only.
Climber.
I saw
learning beside
>> this way.
>> Unlike Furba Wangchu, Sushant is able to
pursue his education. [music]
Still, the mountain compels him.
But the truth is that the future for
guides on Everest is unclear.
>> The craftsmen at this factory supply the
world's top ballerinas with one of their
most important pieces of equipment,
their shoes.
This is how a professional ballerina
customizes her pointe shoes for a show.
>> Destroy them basically. To everybody
else, it looks like we're destroying
them. Just banging it out a little bit.
It's actually kind of fun. I enjoy it
kind of.
>> But after just one day of rehearsing and
performing leaps, turns, and pirouettes,
the shoes will be completely unusable.
>> This is a used shoe.
>> That's why New York City ballet dancers
go through about 7,000 pairs every year.
And all of them come from Freed
of London,
which has been one of the world's
leading ballet shoe manufacturers
for nearly 80 years.
>> We supply all over the world.
There really isn't a country that we
don't work with in some capacity.
>> Its methods haven't changed much over
the decades.
Every single shoe still has to be formed
and stitched mostly by hand.
But this traditional approach makes it
hard to keep up with the non-stop demand
from some of the largest ballet
companies in the world.
>> We are constantly playing catch-up.
>> The New York City Ballet buys all its
shoes from Freed of London,
one of the first companies to customize
shoes to dancers' feet back in 1929.
>> Mr. Freed had been a point shoe maker
for another company, and he wasn't very
satisfied with how the shoes were being
produced. Before Mr. Freed, the point
shoe was very much one size, one width.
So, a dancer had to squeeze their foot
into it. And he came up with this
concept, [music] which seems so normal
today, of making different width
fittings.
>> They all start with stapling a leather
sole to a mold.
>> And this is where the consistency comes
in here.
Just make sure they're all the same.
>> Shoemakers like Alan Doherty make custom
shoes for specific dancers. [music]
He's currently assigned to more than 600
ballerinas.
>> He is really one of our most popular
makers.
>> But the factory only has 24 shoemakers
who make customs, and they supply some
of the largest ballet companies in the
world, including the Royal Ballet in
London, the American Ballet Theatre, and
the Paris Opera Ballet.
>> We are constantly playing catch up. Many
of our pointe shoe makers, their work
schedule is booked right through to the
end of 2026.
When a maker retires, um we start
planning nearly 2 years in advance where
we start to look at what other makers um
are similar in their characteristic of
shoe
and looking at how we can transfer and
move dancers from one maker to the
other.
>> Still, Freed manages to pump out about
2,500 pairs a week.
Most of the process is done by hand.
>> Now, here comes the messy bit.
>> [laughter]
>> The founder of the company, Frederick
Freed himself, created the paste that
makes up the box, which the company
keeps secret.
>> It's specially with flour and water
and a few
secret ingredients, which I'm not
allowed to tell you.
It's like putting your hand in porridge.
>> The paste is what makes the shoes so
malleable, adapting to the exact shape
of a dancer's foot, but it's also why
they wear out so quickly.
Alan can make 34 pairs in a single day.
>> So, everyone makes different amounts. Um
some make [music] 28, some make 30, some
make 32.
Others make 34, one does 41.
>> Putting in the pleats is the hardest and
most crucial step.
>> What does this consist of? It's twist
and pull.
That's what
gives them the strength, the pleats.
We try and be precise as best we can.
It is a handmade job, so it can't be
perfect all the time. Now, they're ready
for stitching.
>> Sewing and stitching are the only steps
where they use machines.
>> Most of our competitors have now closed
their home or native production and
moved offshore and gone into a much more
automated sort of machine-made approach.
But, we still are true to the beginning
idea, which is hand-making shoes,
>> [music]
>> bespoke-ing shoes, giving the dancer
what they need.
>> Once the shoes are made, they have to be
maintained and fitted, and that's where
the dance company's shoe department
comes in.
The New York City Ballet spends nearly a
million dollars a year buying pointe
shoes for its dancers.
And Daniel Wong is the only one keeping
track of them all.
>> Right now, I have about
9,000 pairs of shoes in this room.
>> A pointe shoe has three main sections:
the box, the vamp, and the shank. Also
known as the sole.
The box is what makes a pointe shoe,
well, a pointe shoe.
It helps create the illusion of a dancer
being on the very tip of their toes.
>> This has a platform right here that the
dancer can stand on.
>> The vamp [music] covers and supports the
toes as they bend.
>> The measurement has to be very precise,
so that it doesn't get in the way.
>> The shank supports the dancer's arch
while on pointe.
>> Strength of the shank can be [music]
different depending on what the dancer
wants. So, really, every single piece of
the shoe can be customized.
>> While a dancer is on pointe, the
pressure on their feet and ankles
feels like 12 times their weight.
So, if the fit of the shoe is even a
little bit off, it could be dangerous.
>> You can injure yourself if you're not
wearing the right shoe. You can injure
yourself if a shoe is too soft for your
foot. So, it's just important to find,
you know, a shoe that fits you really
well.
>> Hello. Hello. Hi. How are you?
>> Good. How are you?
>> I'm good.
>> Dancers have preferences.
My job is to make sure that they have
shoes that they're comfortable with, but
also don't get them injured.
>> Which one should we start with?
>> We're going to do a 4 and 1/2. You pin
Does the heel secure?
>> I wouldn't mind raising it. I wouldn't
say no to that.
Wow. See, I like that. That's so much
more comfortable.
>> Okay.
>> Finding the perfect fit can take years,
and dancers go through many trial pairs
before landing on the right ones.
>> Oh, yeah. That's so much better.
>> It's so much better, and I feel better
in them.
>> You can kind of see there's like a 90°
angle.
I don't know how to show it, but there's
like a 90° angle. That's like one of the
customizations that I really like, just
cuz standing on it and then rolling up
to point is feels a lot better. I've
already had a few customs come in with
these specs, meaning like the size and
how short I wanted it.
>> Which one is that?
>> This is without cutting it. This is the
4 and 1/2.
>> 4 and 1/2, but the but the
>> But this trial pair still isn't perfect.
>> If I can do this,
it's a little bit too loose. She'll be
able to wear them,
but you know, they're not they're not
the best. It's not the best fit.
>> [music]
>> For brands to stand out, color is key.
And to get an exact match every [music]
time, companies need printers and ink
mixers who rely on Pantone guides.
For printers, [music] Pantone is a fact
of life.
>> The whole 38 years I've been here, we've
been using Pantone.
If we went away from Pantone, a lot of
our higher end clients, I don't think
they would want to do business with us
anymore.
>> Kevin uses [music] Pantone guides to
verify that printed colors match client
orders.
>> If they have a book and they pick the
color, then we have our book and we know
exactly what they want. They're one of
our most valuable tools that we have in
in industry.
>> Allied Printing mixes each Pantone color
[music] in-house using a set of base
inks.
>> If you mix to the formula, you're
getting the Pantone color. [music] Where
if you're just shooting in the dark, you
could be mixing ink all day long.
>> Anthony is Allied Printing's resident
ink mixer.
>> Just go to page 65, find your color.
This is 711 right here.
So, we want a 6-pounder. Usually I do my
6-pounders in a 1-gallon. This fits up
to like 8 lb.
This is my recipe right here. So, I have
transparent white, which is clear.
We have yellow.
We have warm red.
This one calls for 4.6 lb.
And then we have black.
All right. So, that's the last
ingredient. Ready to throw it on the
mixer.
>> But Allied Printing doesn't buy ink from
Pantone. It works with a licensed
manufacturer.
And to access color formulas, Anthony
uses third-party software that's again
licensed by Pantone.
The only thing Allied Printing buys from
Pantone are the guidebooks.
After mixing, Anthony tests every batch
to ensure it's consistent. [music]
>> I'll put down my sample first, and then
this is my batch.
>> [music]
>> Draw it down.
There's your color.
It looks good. The formula looks good,
and that's it. That's a [music] typical
ink order fulfilled.
>> Because Pantone colors are pre-mixed
from 11 base inks. They look brighter
and cleaner compared to CMYK,
which uses just four colors. [music]
>> Pantone has a huge gamut of colors that
you'll never be able to achieve with
CMYK.
You can try to imitate Pantone colors
through four-color process, but in my
opinion, you never do.
They get dingy and dirty. [music]
>> CMYK is useful for something like this
photo
with hundreds of slightly [music]
different colors and shades.
Pantone excels when you need one solid
color to look exactly [music]
the same every time it's printed, like
with a logo or a brand color.
>> We could run a part of a project here in
Connecticut and someone else could run
part of a project in California, and if
you're running Pantone, they're going to
match.
>> But depending on what you're printing,
Pantone is often more expensive. Besides
the effort of mixing colors, Kevin says
the ink itself costs [music] about 15 to
25% more than CMYK.
>> Some of our customers don't care about
price.
A lot of big corporations, if that's
their corporate color, they want their
corporate color to be perfect. [music]
>> Over in Louisiana, shrimpers are an
important part of the state's history.
Shrimp is the most consumed seafood in
the United States, and in Louisiana,
it's big business.
>> [music]
>> The wild caught crustaceans bring in
about $1.3 billion for the state every
year.
But for the last few years, shrimpers
have been hit with a perfect storm of
rising fuel costs and rock-bottom
[music] prices.
>> That's one of the toughest jobs you
could ever do. And if you're not getting
your dues for it, why do it?
>> Producers say a flood of cheaper
imported shrimp from India and Ecuador
is sinking Louisiana's industry.
But, there's no way to feed America's
skyrocketing demand without imports,
which make up 90% of the shrimp the US
[music] consumes.
Up against these headwinds, companies up
and down Louisiana's supply chain are
closing up shop.
>> If you worked hard and you did the right
thing, you could become a millionaire in
the '80s and the '90s.
Now, you can barely make a living.
>> So, how [snorts] did the industry get
this bad? And is it too late to save it?
Kristen Balmer is one of the few
processors left in the area who only
works with Gulf shrimp.
Just like his family has for over 130
years.
>> We've definitely seen a lot of
processors go out of business. It's
become more of a volume game because the
margins are so tight.
>> His company processes 30 million pounds
of shrimp annually.
>> So, what we're doing is easy peeling
shrimp. We're hand-feeding it into a
machine that puts a and that splits the
back of the shell, cuts the shell open,
and then it allows when you cook it more
flavor to get into the shrimp as well as
making it easier to peel.
>> Kristen's team flash freezes all the
crustaceans in this room. That's how
they're able to transport the shrimp all
over the country.
>> So, they're cooking shrimp for the
second time to make sure they get all
the defects out of it before it goes up.
>> This shaker separates the pieces so they
won't stick together when they're
frozen.
Then they take a trip down this tunnel
at minus 400° Fahrenheit.
>> And after the shrimp it gets the liquid
nitrogen it forms a crystal on the
shrimp and then it moves slowly through
the belt to freeze from the outside in.
Don't stick your finger in unless you
have a warrant that you want to burn
off.
>> This machine portions the seafood into
5-lb bags of about 15 pieces.
Each bag gets a traceability barcode.
>> Link it all the way back to the shrimp
dock that it came from.
>> This processed product comes out to
anywhere from 7 to $10 a pound,
depending on the season.
>> With inflation, everything is getting
more and more expensive, and running
these [music] processing plants and all
this movement of equipment and avoiding
breakdowns takes a lot of capital.
>> [music]
>> Meanwhile, shrimpers like Captain Lonnie
Mayeux Jr. are facing skyrocketing costs
of operating a boat.
>> You're wasting fuel and ice if you don't
catch anything.
>> Since the 1980s, he says a block of ice
has gone from [music] $14 to $26 today.
A set of new nets more than doubled, and
a gallon of gas [music] more than
tripled in price.
At 82 years old, Lonnie, who goes by
Knuckles, hasn't given up trawling these
waters even after six decades. [music]
Starting in May, he heads out to catch
brown shrimp, usually around sunset.
>> You have to go uh do your homework and
so,
and know where they're going to be at.
>> He works independently, like [music]
most of the shrimpers here.
>> Right about there.
Uh
a little too far.
>> During the day, brown shrimp may bury
themselves in the sediment to hide from
predators.
But after dark, they often [music] come
out and roam in shallow water.
Knuckles and his deckhand Steve drop
these nets that skim the top of the
water.
>> We're not dragging anything on the
bottom.
>> He positions himself against the
current, so the shrimp flow right into
his nets.
>> The shrimp
are not like fish.
They can't really swim that great.
They take the They take a ride on the
current.
>> Knuckles and Steve will pick out and
keep just the shrimp.
Sea turtles have an escape hatch in the
net, and other animals get thrown back
into the sea.
Where some dolphins are waiting to chow
down on them.
>> If we don't pick up in that favor often
enough, they'll take and bite it out of
the net.
>> They can literally rip a a 4-ft hole in
it, which is going to take a lot of time
to fix.
>> Like this one, Knuckles pulls up the net
so he can sew it closed.
>> You're going to lose everything.
You know?
You're going to be working for literally
nothing.
>> This work can be grueling.
Some shrimpers have big enough vessels,
they can stay out for weeks at a time.
Knuckles has a smaller boat, so he
fishes just until morning.
>> Well, it keeps you in shape.
>> But even after all this work, there's a
chance they could have a bad run.
Tonight, most of the nets were full of
catfish.
>> Ooh, catfish.
>> See the belly?
It's full of shrimp.
>> Full of shrimp.
They went in the net, ate all the
shrimp.
And you got a pound of shrimp, it's all
catfish.
I'm going to try pushing up going a
little further up in the lake or
something.
>> Knuckles spent $45,000 buying and fixing
up his boat. It was meant to be his
ticket to retirement.
But now he's unsure that plan will work.
>> You know, for me to get out of the
business, I got to sell it. I got no
retirement.
But I can't sell a boat. Can't give it
away.
Nobody wants it.
>> And most shrimpers agree, it's getting
harder to justify going out.
>> When this boat leaves the dock, it's
going to cost me over $1,000.
It's killing us. The farmers, it's
killing us.
>> Right now, nobody want to do it no more
because they're struggling.
>> Molena Chee has been fishing for 8
years.
>> [music]
>> Like 60% of the state's shrimp boat
owners, she and her husband are
originally from Southeast Asia.
>> With our education, there's nothing else
we could do besides fishermen,
especially like me and my husband like
in our mid-50s.
>> Milena and her husband weren't able to
go to college, but they hope shrimping
would help their kids do the opposite.
[music]
>> Not enough to pay, especially when you
have two kids in college. You're
struggling.
>> [music]
>> Dock owners are feeling the impact, too.
>> Cuz if we don't bring no shrimp, they
don't make no money, either.
You know, when the shrimp boat go out,
they're going to kill the docks, too.
That's a pretty shrimp.
>> Dean Blanchard's family has been buying
and selling local shrimp for five
generations. [music]
>> Uh I was born in a shrimp dock. When I
was a baby, they used to put me in a
shrimp box.
>> His dock, 2 hours south of New Orleans,
was once one of the biggest shrimp
suppliers in the country.
But last year, he paid the lowest prices
he ever has for the larger shrimp.
>> 30 some years ago, they went down from
$5 to $1.30.
>> That's because he's selling it for so
little to the peeling factories.
>> Right now, the cheapest I've ever seen
in my life.
I'm sick to my stomach. I ain't never
seen nothing like this.
Never. Never in my life seen it this
bad.
>> After six decades in the industry,
Dean's no stranger to financial
challenges.
From the 2010 BP oil spill to big
storms.
His dock had $2 million in damages after
Hurricane Ida hit in 2021.
>> Yeah, where you standing right there
wasn't even there after the storm. I
mean, I've rebuilt this building at
least eight, nine times.
>> He never fixed up this part of his
marina.
>> Uh it brings tears to your eyes. I mean,
everything you worked for all your life
is gone.
>> But imports, he says, done even more
damage.
>> We're directly correlated with imports.
If a completely processed product is
coming in for just over $4 a pound, uh
that means our dockside prices have to
be lower, the processors prices are
lower. So,
to be able to try to get that market
share [music] and keep it. So, you're
making the same amount of money that you
would in 2000,
but 22 years [music] later.
>> Fewer boats can afford to go out, so
less shrimp [music] is landing on Dean's
dock.
>> We're down to right under 20% of what we
normally are for this time of the year.
>> On this day we visited in May 2023, not
a single shrimp boat pulled up to
unload.
>> It ain't going to last too much longer
like this.
Thank God I'm almost 65 years old and I
ain't got no kids in this business.
>> Dean estimates that 96% of the docks
operating when he started out have since
closed [music] down.
>> I feel bad for the people because I know
once I'm gone, they're going to have to
drive 50, 60, 70 miles to go sell their
product.
>> Just like Knuckles, when Dean retires,
he doesn't [music] think anyone will buy
the company.
>> Nobody can afford to take it over. The
property is worth more than the
business.
>> [music]
>> The workers here use some of the finest
pigments in the world [music] to create
colored pencils that can cost around
$350 a set.
>> Every colored pencil starts off like
this, bright, powdery pigment.
But, it's the secret recipe for
transforming these pigments into
colorful cores that sets professional
pencils apart from student grade ones.
Every ingredient, from pigments to waxes
and oils, and even the wood is carefully
chosen to make these pencils perform
better on paper.
And artists are often willing to shell
out hundreds of dollars for this level
of performance.
At Faber-Castell's factory in Stein,
Germany, workers churn out a whopping
2.3 billion pencils a year. [music]
Making them takes a surprising amount of
precision. Starting with these, the
pigments.
Just like [music] people, the particles
of each pigment have their own distinct
personality and behavior.
Some are rough and edgy [music] and
scratch across the paper,
while others are smooth and silky.
But size also matters, down to the
micrometer.
Faber-Castell says ideally, 90% of the
pigment particles should have a diameter
of less than 40 micrometers.
It says this is perfect for creating a
core with a consistent texture and
vibrant color that applies smoothly.
Balancing the pigments' behavior
requires adjusting the other
ingredients. Unlike cheaper
alternatives, professional colored
pencils have a lot more pigment than
filler, so it's important that the
balance of ingredients is just right.
The ingredients are top secret, but
Gerold Luga, a chemist at Faber-Castell,
told Business Insider it's a specific
combination of oils, waxes, and fillers
that binds the pigments.
The result is this mixture, dough-like
clumps of color.
But each color has a bespoke formula
because not all pigments are created
equal.
After the mysterious blend of waxes,
oils, and fillers is mixed with the
pigment, it's pushed through this
high-pressure machine.
The result, identical pencil length
cylindrical cores.
Workers bake the cores in batches to
harden them.
Then, they dip the dry cores in a melted
mixture of waxes and fatty acid
derivatives.
Faber-Castell's colored pencil cores are
3.8 mm in diameter, making them less
likely to break compared to Crayola's
3.3 mm cores.
The company randomly tests cores from
each batch to make sure they won't break
under pressure.
Quality testers apply pressure to the
cores at a 60° angle.
They shouldn't break until the force is
at least 3.3 kg.
The core's performance is also
scrutinized with smear tests like this
one.
>> [music]
>> Pencil cores made by different brands
each have their own characteristics.
The wax base of Caran d'Ache's Luminance
pencils is soft, so the color melts into
the paper.
That makes them great for creating
gradients.
Faber-Castell's colored pencils, on the
other hand, have a harder core, so
they're best for fine lines and
realistic details.
Even the wood encasing the cores of
professional-grade pencils is carefully
considered.
A pencil's wood determines how long the
pencil will last and how well it will
sharpen.
At the factory, the cedar is cut into
planks, which are stored for months
until they're dry.
Grooves are milled into the wood and the
cores are slotted into the planks.
Another identical plank is glued on top
and they're pressed together before the
next machine cuts them into perfect
pencils.
But the pencils shouldn't just perform
well, they must also look and feel
expensive.
Workers mix dyes to the exact color of
the cores to create a water-based
varnish for the outside of the pencils.
Another machine coats each pencil with
this varnish.
The pencils are then stamped with a
company's branding and the end caps are
dipped again,
rounding out the top of the pencil.
Every step of the way, the pencils are
checked for visual defects like chips
and varnish irregularities, and the
faulty ones are removed.
The longevity of a color is known as its
light fastness.
Faber-Castell uses a star rating where
three stars means the color will be
preserved with little or no fading for
100 years in museum-like conditions.
Almost all of the colored pencils the
company offers in its professional lines
are three stars.
Each color receives a rating through a
specialized light fastness test.
>> [music]
>> At the world's largest truck stop,
there's no shortage of jobs, which is
why Iowa 80 is dubbed the Disney World
for truckers.
This kitchen feeds the world's largest
truck stop.
Chefs sling out 350,000
meals a year.
Iowa 80 covers over 150 football fields.
It's one of the last major US truck
stops that's independently owned and
thriving.
Truckers come from all over for its
movie theater, truck wash, chiropractor,
dentist, and 900 parking spots for
semi's alone. [music]
>> It is impossible to find a place to park
in other truck stops. There's always
spaces to park here.
>> But most of America's mom-and-pop truck
stops are gone or barely hanging on.
>> So this is what truck stops used to look
like. It has a gas station, a cafe, and
lodging.
>> Reed and Island Corner in Colo, Iowa is
one of America's last remaining one
stops from the early 1900s.
It sits at the intersection of two of
America's first cross-country [music]
highways, Route 30, which carried
travelers through small towns like Colo.
>> They're so vital to our community and
our state.
>> But when the interstate carved new paths
around Colo, the once constant flow of
travelers disappeared.
Now a few people from the town are
trying to save it.
>> We don't have any money. We're starting
with zero.
>> So how did American truck stops go from
this to this?
And as more professional drivers hit the
road, why are truck stops so important?
The Iowa 80 kitchen runs 24/7, [music]
365 days a year.
I got there around 8:00 a.m. on a
Friday, just in time for the morning
rush.
Chefs were slinging out pancakes and
French toast to order, making all the
food for the 50-ft buffet, and working
the omelet [music] bar.
>> There's a lot of calling out to each
other.
Kind of like a rhythmic dance or
something like that.
>> They're expecting 600 people today. So,
chefs tackle prep for lunch and dinner
early in the morning, too.
>> When we're, you know, full steam, we'll
have 20 workers probably today.
>> Bacon is the first thing to hit the
ovens.
>> We usually prep up about 60 lbs of bacon
for the day.
>> Since opening 61 years ago, Iowa 80
Kitchen has served up to 23 million
eggs.
Scrambled eggs for the buffet arrive
frozen.
Chefs defrost the bags and drop them in
a vat of hot water to steam.
>> And then we just beat them up with the
whisk and then we serve them.
>> Head chef Rick Denney plans out how much
food the team will make depending on the
day and season.
>> How are you related to the family?
>> I'm not related at all. I've tried
marrying in a few times, but they won't
let me. Uh, this is
>> My grandfather was the original owner of
the restaurant.
>> Chris Honn [music] still uses her
grandfather's recipe for meatloaf, a
crowd favorite.
She chops onions and celery and dumps in
spices and tomato sauce for the base of
the meatloaf. [music]
>> We got 90 lbs of ground beef here.
The three main components are the beef,
the mixture there, and then the
breadcrumbs.
How many years has this been used?
>> 40.
>> 40 years? Yep.
>> This mixer is older than I am.
>> This is enough meatloaf to last two to
three days. So, chefs portion it into
tubs.
>> So, this won't get baked until probably
tomorrow. We bake uh two off a day.
>> For Iowa 80 [music] Kitchen size, chefs
make a surprising amount from scratch.
Like their ranch dressing.
>> [music]
>> With 6 gallons of buttermilk,
60 lbs of mayo,
and nine packets of ranch seasoning.
>> to try spreading it around.
>> Iowa 80 staff also hand-bread and dunk
their fried chicken, one of the most
popular dishes.
Come 11:00 a.m., they flip the buffet
over to lunch. [music]
Most of the people who stop in to eat
are professional drivers who spend
months at a time on the road.
>> They enjoy being able to come in and
get, you know, a a home-cooked meal.
>> It's tiring.
We drive 11 hours a day, have a 70-hour
work week, and I always stop here
because I like to shop, I like the food
[music] court. It's one of my favorite
truck stops.
>> A lot of people eat three decent meals a
day. Well, we're lucky to get one.
>> Jerry Lenander has been driving a truck
for nearly 50 years.
>> Highway 80 is the real deal.
I mean, you can sit down for a
home-cooked hamburger steak meal.
>> But there's a lot more than food here.
>> We have movie theater, we have a driver
lounge that has a big TV.
>> We toured the space with Lee Meyer, the
founder's granddaughter, and the third
generation working here.
>> Our philosophy is that when our
customers are at home, they should be
with their family, not running all these
errands or doing laundry, getting a
haircut, things like that.
>> There's also a gym, a chapel, [music]
and 24 private showers.
There's even a dentist on site.
>> If they're having an emergency on the
road, they're not going to be able to
pull their truck and trailer [music]
into, like, my dentist's office, you
know, in in a town.
>> They still have the mom-and-pop feel,
and it's just it's kind of out of the
norm.
>> You can get your truck washed,
your dog washed,
or your vehicle serviced.
>> It's a trucker's truck stop, trust me.
>> So, you said that we can Thank you. Uh
order anything all day, right?
>> Thank you. Yes, 24 hours a day,
breakfast, lunch, or dinner. So.
>> on the menu.
>> I know, it's a big menu.
>> Meaning you can get this giant breakfast
plate at 3:00 p.m. like we did.
>> Okay, so you said that this is a fan
favorite.
>> Oh, yeah, the hungry man big deal.
>> People finish this?
>> I bet they do. I don't know that I've
ever seen it, but here we go.
>> Big dude is coming off a truck with a
huge appetite after 10 hours of driving.
I could [music] see this being a fan
favorite, for sure.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, I actually think I like the
sausage better than I like the bacon.
The pancakes though, they're made with
sweet cream instead of buttermilk and
they had the perfect amount of tang to
sweetness. That's the best thing on the
table. Because they there is a crunch.
Even with all the syrup, there's a
little crunch. But gooey in the middle.
Rivaling those pancakes was the
meatloaf. That had a lot of gravy.
Let me get a Let me get a good bite.
It feels like when you're a kid and your
mom makes meatloaf. That's not a joke.
Midwest just coziness right there. We
did come here a lot of Sundays after
church with my grandparents. So yeah,
this is like home cooking for me.
>> [laughter]
>> Prepping footballs for NFL and college
games is a job in itself and one that
can get dirty.
>> Dan Colson's job is to break in new
footballs for quarterbacks on NFL and
college teams.
He uses conditioners,
heat guns,
and mud from New Jersey riverbanks.
>> Getting the leather the way you want it
to is an art form in itself. But just a
few decades ago, pro players [music]
couldn't always use these customized
footballs in games.
Then in 2006, Tom Brady and Peyton
Manning helped convince the NFL to
change the rules.
That inspired teams across America to
start testing new ways to customize
footballs, too.
But getting one ball ready can take
days.
>> [music]
>> So some teams hire outside specialists
like Dan.
Today, he and his wife Emily work out of
their home in Bayonne, New Jersey.
Slathering thousands of balls per
season, even for the Super Bowl.
>> Smells like a swamp down here. It's
terrible.
>> So why do some teams spend tens of
thousands of dollars a year on mudded
footballs?
And what does it take [music] to get
them all to the field.
Dan started Gridiron Football Prep in
2021 after losing his job at Wilson
Sporting Goods.
He's in the middle of 48 balls for Ohio
State, the country's most valuable
college football program. Worth roughly
$2 billion.
>> They've really championed this process
of really making a ball that is
conducive to their quarterback. So, what
we do is we'll get the ball,
come over here,
get our brush that we use.
So, you want to brush in circles because
the grain of the leather might be
slightly different per panel. What
you're doing is you're kind of opening
the pores of the actual leather itself.
>> Dan applies his own custom leather
conditioner, which adds moisture and
grip.
Then, he uses an infrared thermometer to
check when it's dried back to room
temperature.
Leather balm loosens and softens the
leather even more.
>> Leather balm is kind of our secret
sauce, if you will. So, as we compare
brand new ball out of the box,
conditioned,
now balmed, ready to be heat gunned.
>> NFL and college footballs are made from
real leather.
One of the reasons they're up to 10
times more expensive than the average
ball at a sporting goods store.
Horween Leather in Chicago has made
leather for nearly every NFL and college
football for the last 70 years.
>> People ask me who I'm rooting for in the
Super Bowl, and it's always the ball.
>> Skip Horween's [music] family opened the
business in 1905.
It's grown from a small shop to a
company with roughly $25 million in
annual sales.
Horween's leather comes from the hides
of steers, which are male cattle raised
for beef.
These hides are stronger and more
flexible than the ones from other
cattle, so they can withstand tough
conditions on football field.
>> [music]
>> We pay a premium for them, and it's
worth it.
>> Roughly 2,500 hides arrive every day
from Iowa and Canada.
Employees grade each one on a scale of 1
to 10.
The lower the number, the better the
quality.
Only grades 1, 2, and 3 are used for
footballs.
>> This particular skin has a bunch of
fairly heavy scratches on it, and that
would not be suitable for top-grade
football skin.
>> Then they throw the hides into drums
filled with tree bark extract, oil, and
waxes.
This transforms them into leather.
Next, a machine squeezes out excess
moisture.
Then workers throw the hides onto glass
panels for 4 hours to dry.
>> So this whole thing is a giant hot air
dryer.
>> Next is the embossing phase, which gives
the football its texture.
A metal press stamps each hide with up
to 1,000 tons of pressure,
so the pebbles don't fade over time.
Horween makes eight kinds of football
leather and another for NBA basketballs.
>> Football is is the grippier of the two
again because you've got your skill
players that need to be able to handle
the ball, whether it's catching,
throwing, snapping, or kicking.
>> Workers spray each hide with up to five
coats of dye to give it a slick finish.
>> All of the football companies we work
with have slightly different pattern and
slightly different finishes.
>> Horween ships about 250,000
sheets of finished leather a year, also
called sides.
Skip says sales are strong now, but he
lost some clients over the years as
cheaper synthetic leather became more
popular.
Fake leather is a $39 billion industry
and expected to nearly double in the
next decade.
>> A lot of those retail balls were leather
at one time, but almost entirely
synthetic now.
>> Skip says making leather for different
industries helps Horween survive tough
times.
>> This might be football leather today and
shoe leather tomorrow and jacket leather
the next day.
Not an easy business, look, none of them
really are, but the idea that I can turn
on a game and see something that I had a
small [music] part in making, I just get
a kick out of it at to this day.
>> Skip delivers leather once a week to Big
Game, a company in Texas that makes
nearly all the footballs for America's
best college programs and 3,000 high
schools.
>> Welcome to the football wonderland.
>> Chris Calandro founded the company in
1993.
>> I'm a nutty professor type and the
things that we can change with a
football
is really limited your imagination.
Very few teams in college football and
high school football use exactly the
same spec that we build.
>> Even the best cuts of Horween leather
have small defects.
So, Big Game starts by cutting around
them.
>> We don't want to build a football
and get to the end of the line and
realize it's got an imperfection on it,
then we pretty much kill the football.
>> Then workers cut it into four panels,
which will form the outer layer of the
ball.
>> These are now married together forever.
>> Unlike NFL teams, colleges are allowed
to use different sized footballs.
>> [music]
>> Big Game makes them in three different
dimensions, depending on the player
they're for.
>> So, we build things [music]
on the larger side if you're a 6'5
pocket passer, or if you're a you know,
5'10 dual threat player, we might have a
smaller ball for you.
Even at this early stage, there's
already been two major customizations
from the quarterback to what size the
ball is going to be,
and the leather that the quarterback
chose.
>> Then they add team logos,
usually by stamping a metal press on a
heated piece of metal foil.
After some extra fabric and stitching,
panels are done.
But right now the football is inside
out,
and it has to be flipped around by hand.
>> If you do it the wrong way, you damage
the ball.
Rodney's doing an outstanding job. It is
a
as much about technique as it is about
strength.
I recently beat Rodney in an arm
wrestling contest.
>> Laces come in multiple textures, and
have to be added by hand, too.
>> Some are kind of have this rubbery feel,
some are sort of have a suede leathery
feel.
It is, I think probably the one thing
that quarterbacks are most passionate
about, um is the way the laces feel.
>> Eventually, workers stick the football
into a wooden mold, where a computerized
pump inflates it.
>> And we're using more pressure than is
allowed so that we can push out all
those seams and rough spots.
>> Big Game makes about a thousand balls a
day, even during the football
off-season.
For $10, an employee will spend a few
hours conditioning a ball to make it
feel broken in.
>> Some little [music] things to help get
it to leather feel great, you know, like
a nice pair of shoes or a bag or
something.
>> But Dan charges up to $70 per ball
because they're customized for specific
players.
>> How do you grip the ball? What do you
like on the ball? Do you want it
tackier? Do you want it softer? Do you
want a combination?
>> Ohio State, his biggest client, flies
him in each season to meet with coaches
and quarterbacks.
>> Ultimately, it comes down to the
quarterback, but there are a lot of
people that are going to have say in it
because they want to be educated, they
want to be on [music] top of it.
>> After Dan's done softening the leather,
he applies heat.
This causes the leather conditioner and
balm to bake into the ball.
>> Too hot, you're going to burn the ball,
dry it out. Not enough, it's going to be
a little gummy. We found that sweet spot
[music] around 650-700 degrees of a heat
gun itself.
>> Then he coats the ball in mud,
which blends all the layers and helps
protect the grip from rain or sweat.
>> And again, bring out that richness color
that so many people like. [music]
I like doing it by hand, making sure
that it's completely being more or less
massaged into the ball and spread evenly
throughout.
Ohio State specifically will ask to try
to keep the stripes as clean as
possible, so we don't mud over those
stripes. That's not for everybody.
>> Dan himself collects this mud from New
Jersey riverbanks.
>> You really want that milkshake thick
milkshake-like consistency.
>> This is also the smelliest part of the
process.
>> It's an awful smell, specifically if
it's raining outside and it's more
humid.
>> It's an acquired smell. I wouldn't
invite people off the street to come
smell it who aren't used to it.
Sometimes it makes you question why you
are working from home, but at the end of
the day it's it's a sign that we're we
have a lot of business and [music] it's
thriving.
>> He lets the mud dry for at least 12
hours.
Then brushes it clean.
An electric brush wheel gets deep into
the ball's crevices.
>> You can just run the ball on the wheel
itself, get that dust off.
>> Then one final layer of conditioner.
There's always those little frustrating
dust spots. This helps
just get that [music] off so that it
gives it a really clean finished look.
>> Now, the 36-hour process is done.
>> You can feel that tack,
but it doesn't have any residue on your
hands.
>> Then they box the balls up and ship
them.
>> [snorts]
>> Shout out to Reuben at UPS and Keith,
my guys.
>> Summer is Gridiron's busiest season, but
demand stays high throughout the year.
>> The amount of footballs depends on the
weather. Rain will kill a football.
Usually a good equipment manager will
have 24 to 48 footballs ready to go, and
then they'll always send me 24 more so
that they're always replenishing.
>> Back in 2005, NFL quarterbacks couldn't
use their own footballs in every game.
The home team supplied all the balls, so
visiting quarterbacks were stuck with
whatever they were given.
>> If I have a ball and I have my hand on
the ball, and it, [music] you know,
maybe that index finger is slipping a
little bit or that thumb is not secure,
right? That's what you're going to be
thinking about.
>> Then in 2006, Tom Brady and Peyton
Manning helped convince the league to
change the rules,
allowing all quarterbacks to use their
own footballs on offense.
This eventually inspired college
programs like Arizona State to take
football prep seriously, too.
The team needs 80 footballs for just one
practice,
and it's essential that every single one
is broken in.
For official games, the team's equipment
manager, Arthur Huzzard, selects 12 of
the quarterbacks' favorites.
>> We give those uh 12 footballs [music] to
the referees, and the referees like
check them, mark them,
and um make sure we can play with those.
>> But do these mudded footballs really
make a difference?
Dam thinks they can help keep players
focused on the game itself.
>> You put on a pair of shoes, you know
they're comfortable because you're not
worried about them. So, our goal is to
have them never think about the security
of the football. When it's in their
hands, it's to what they want it to be.
>> But he says he can't substitute for game
preparation.
>> Guy throws a perfect spiral in the
corner of the end zone, he probably
threw that ball well before he had a
ball prepared. But, if there's a
comfortability to them, hey, maybe I had
something to do with it.
The strangest preference I've ever
gotten is somebody who literally told me
that the ball smelled funny, and that it
bothered him when he had it up on his uh
you know uh ready to throw, and that he
was wondering if I could do anything to
help him with that. So, we got creative,
and we literally put like a essential
oil in the in the mud, and we're like
mixing it in, so that it had a nicer
aroma to it.
>> Cafeterias were once a culinary staple
of the American South. And even though
running one is hard work, some owners
are aiming to mount a comeback.
>> This 70-year-old cafeteria feeds [music]
5,000 people a week.
Michael Green is the third-generation
owner of Matthew's cafeteria [music]
in Tucker, Georgia.
>> 10 lbs of macaroni, which makes 200
servings. And that's about the smallest
batch I'll make.
>> In the early 1900s, while diners [music]
defined the American Northeast, the
South had its own institution,
cafeterias.
>> Anybody of a certain age grew up
>> [music]
>> in the South eating at a cafeteria.
>> At their peak, thousands operated
nationwide with chains like Morrison's
and Luby's popping up all over the
South.
>> There's actually a section [music] of
the phone book
for cafeterias.
>> It is mostly like a Sunday thing. Get
out of church, got the kids, [music]
let's go to the cafeteria.
>> But in the '90s, cafeteria lines started
to dry up and many chains shuttered.
>> It's not just about food, it's about a
community.
>> For the surviving cafeterias, rising
restaurant prices might be sending
customers back their way.
>> As fast food prices keep rising,
consumers are looking for better value.
Sit-down restaurants with bigger
portions start to make more sense.
>> I went to Georgia to find out why these
restaurants are getting harder to find
and to learn how one of the state's
oldest cafeterias, and one of its
newest, are fighting to keep their hot
bar steaming and communities fed.
>> This is a really, really hard way to
make a living.
>> Let that basket do the work. There you
go.
>> Matthews cafeteria opened up in Tucker,
Georgia in 1955.
At the time, the Atlanta suburb was
becoming a manufacturing hub and workers
stopped [music] in on their lunch
breaks.
>> To the basement.
>> Michael is still serving them many of
his grandfather's original dishes.
>> We don't even write down recipes.
There's nothing written down here.
>> Like these biscuits that [music] Chef
Maria has hand mixed and cut for 24
years.
The mac and cheese was Michael's
grandmother's recipe.
>> Her macaroni was spongy. It was
casserole-like.
This is going to be a bit overcooked in
some people's eyes, but that's how my
grandmother did it.
Al dente is not a Southern American
word. [music] We are not cooking this al
dente.
10 lb of pasta, 8 lb of cheese, which is
the perfect ratio, I think.
Looks like a lot of milk, but this is a
lot of macaroni. [music]
You got to learn to be ambidextrous in
the kitchen or you will wear one arm
out, I can tell you that.
>> On the other side of the kitchen, chefs
tackle a crowd favorite, the chicken
[music] and dumplings.
>> She's cutting them now and letting them
toughen up just a tad.
It just gives them a little more
resiliency when they go into the boiling
broth.
>> Michael's juggling a massive scale with
100 items on the menu each week.
He also has to choose dishes that'll
stay tasty for hours on a steam table, a
classic cafeteria feature. [music]
Take this rice, for example. Michael
steam cooks it like you would pasta with
extra water. That way it stays fluffy.
Michael's also working within the
confines of a cramped, nearly
century-old building.
>> It was not built to be a restaurant.
Some of my relatives lived here at one
point, then it was a general store.
>> Instead of running food up the narrow
steps to the restaurant, chefs rely on
this old dumbwaiter from the 1950s.
>> And the dumbwaiter was not electric at
first. It had counterweights. It was
done by hand. Better than walking it up
the steps.
>> But even with this old layout, the staff
has to keep the restaurant running for
15 hours a day, from 5:00 a.m. to 8:00
p.m.
They open that early for the factory
workers who start at 6:00.
>> It fills a void for people, you know?
Nowhere else to get breakfast.
>> Do you all come here often?
>> Yeah, every day.
>> Uh, it's been going on 50 years, 50
years.
>> You have a little breakfast club, I love
it.
Unlike the
>> which usually charge a flat fee for
unlimited food, cafeterias charge per
item.
As you slide your tray down, you pick
what you want and pay for what's on your
plate. Look at this bread.
What's really impressive is all of this
was like less than $15.
Look at this. You have the nice crust on
the outside, but it's soft and pillowy
on the inside. I mean, come on. It's so
good.
Mhm.
This is like a three-handed job.
Mhm. And some biscuits and gravy. Oh my
god, look at the sheen on that.
Mhm. That biscuit stayed crunchy. I feel
like they figured out the science of
still being yummy, but
>> [music]
>> sitting out.
I used to stop at cafeterias on road
trips when I was a kid, and this feels
very familiar and very homey. Even
though I just got here, I just feel sort
of like wrapped up in this coziness of a
giant biscuit sandwich and a big pile of
sausage gravy.
But the day is just getting started.
In 3 hours, hundreds of people will show
up for the lunch rush.
And Matthews [music] changes its menu
every single day.
On the Tuesday we visited, Michael was
finishing up the barbecue pork,
slow-cooked outback for 12 [music]
hours.
>> Almost falling apart. Almost. That is
some good barbecue right there. This is
for you. These are the best little bits.
I don't know why they always stick to
the great.
>> Wow. [music]
>> The sugar almost gets candy-like on the
outside. Yeah.
>> That's a beautiful crust to it.
Friday is for his wife Jenna's chicken
and rice casserole.
>> It was so good that we added it to the
menu, and I took it and multiplied it by
1,000. I mean, literally.
>> This is a
>> Michael actually met his wife here 14
years ago during a lunch service.
>> On the other side of that pole is a
plaque that says where Jenna met
Michael.
And that's where I proposed to her.
>> But it's not just his wife who has kept
Michael coming back [music] all these
years.
>> I hated this place as a kid. I didn't
want to go to work
in the summer. My friends weren't
working. [music] They were at the pool.
>> How's lunch?
>> And then you get old enough to listen to
people when they tell you how special,
for [music] whatever reason, this place
is to them.
And now I get it.
>> Got to get a spoon.
>> I love to cook.
The steam, the sounds, the smells, the
energy, and the people I get to work
with every day.
I love these guys. I do.
Hey.
>> What's serving?
>> Love you, man.
>> I was even more impressed with the lunch
menu.
Can you hear that?
Nice and crispy.
The chicken is still tender inside. Next
[music] up, I'm going to try these
chicken and dumplings.
Oh, that's so cozy.
And they let the dumplings firm up so
that there's a nice kind of like chew to
them.
My favorite thing on the table?
That mac and cheese.
Yeah.
Slaps.
That's like childhood mac and cheese. I
can see why this is one of their crowd
favorites. [music]
Both of these trays, for myself and my
camera guy, were $47 including desserts.
Look at that crust.
And then, strawberry shortcake.
That's really good. It's pretty
impressive that so much of this is made
from scratch. Cuz it's not like that big
of a kitchen, you know?
And I wasn't the only one enjoying it.
Retired police officer Mike Reagan comes
in with all his friends from the force
every week.
>> It's kind of like a a community
gathering place in Tucker. Tucker's
still got that small family feel.
Like small town.
And when you [music] come in here and
eating, a lot of people you might not
sit with and talk to but they always say
hey. They always say hi.
>> That community feel is part of why
cafeterias were so successful to begin
with.
But they didn't start in the South.
The earliest recorded one popped up in
New York City in 1885, right across from
the stock exchange. [music]
Brokers ate and then paid for their food
on the honor system.
In the 1890s, at an exposition in
Chicago, the restaurant style was named
cafeterias, borrowing the Spanish word
for coffee shop, cafeterías.
In 1906, the first California [music]
cafeteria chain, Boos Brothers, opened
up.
By 1927, it had six locations in Los
Angeles. It was nicknamed the cafeteria
trail.
Then the cafeterias started taking over
the Southern US.
They fit the old-fashioned home-style
cooking already preferred in the region.
Their audience only grew after World War
II as the South [music] urbanized around
textile mills, car and airplane
factories, and shipyards.
Cafeterias became a go-to for workers
who needed cheap, filling meals on tight
schedules.
The food was on full display, cutting
down on customer complaints.
Things were cooked in bulk to bring down
the cost per serving.
And the line was set up so high-margin
sides like [music] desserts and salads
came first, encouraging customers to
load up their trays before reaching
lower-margin main dishes like meats.
Morrison's opened [music] up in 1920 and
would become one of the biggest
cafeteria chains in America.
Followed by chains like S&S in Georgia,
K&W in North Carolina,
>> [music]
>> Piccadilly in Louisiana, and Luby's in
Texas.
On Sundays, Southern cafeterias filled
up with families after [music] church.
>> Get out of church, got the kids, let's
go to the cafeteria.
>> By the 1960s, [music] cafeterias were
all over malls, downtowns, and shopping
centers in the South.
But there was tension brewing.
Cafeterias were segregated in the Jim
Crow South.
In 1961, protesters staged [music] a
sit-in at the Anna Maud cafeteria in
Oklahoma City.
In 1964, dozens of black Tennesseans
were arrested for protesting a
whites-only Morrison's in Nashville.
The chain didn't change its whites-only
policy until after the Civil Rights Act
was passed, banning segregation in
public spaces.
Soon, cafeterias faced big competition
[music]
from fast food.
By the mid-70s, McDonald's and Burger
King had hundreds of locations.
They were cheaper than a cafeteria line,
and they had convenient drive-thrus.
>> And they have buying power. They can
offer a sausage biscuit [music] for a
dollar. I can't. It's like the
mom-and-pop hardware store competing
with Home Depot.
>> Cafeterias also felt pressure from
casual dining [music] chains like
Chili's and Applebee's,
which expanded rapidly in suburban
America in the '80s and '90s.
Then mall traffic began [music] to slow,
drying up the dependable crowds that had
sustained cafeterias for decades.
Many cafeterias tried to cut costs,
switching from fresh ingredients to
canned and frozen ones,
but they lost loyal customers when the
quality worsened.
Business was so tough that big cafeteria
chains began consolidating and closing.
Piccadilly bought Morrison's.
In 2020, Luby's almost went under, but a
new owner managed to save 32 locations.
In 2022, Piccadilly bought another
chain, K&W. [music]
But 3 years later it shut down all the
remaining locations.
Piccadilly itself went from 270
locations in 1998 to fewer than 30
today.
>> The family, everything, [music] yes,
tradition, all that is gone. All that
went out the window.
>> It breaks my heart.
>> It's sad. It's sad to see things
fade into history.
>> But a newer cafeteria, down the road
from Matthews, is proving they're not
all dinosaurs.
When a nearby S&S Cafeteria shuttered
after 43 years in business, Lewis
Squires bought its old equipment.
>> I was so heartbroken by it. I thought I
could rescue it.
>> He opened the Magnolia Room, featuring
the refurbished cafeteria line, in 2017.
It has higher prices, a more upscale
feel than Matthews, and a wait staff.
Plus, it's not open for breakfast.
But the kitchen was still buzzing on a
cold Wednesday morning.
>> You feel the pressure? Okay.
>> [laughter]
>> All right, 3 minutes on that lasagna.
>> And head chef, Deborah Tardiff, is at
the helm of it all.
>> All right, Serilla, we got all the bread
out?
>> Yeah, it's full.
>> It's full. Thank you, baby. Thank you so
much. Green beans, pinto beans, collard
greens, beets. I started cooking when I
was 9 years old. So, this is my [music]
passion. It comes just like walking now.
>> She has to keep everyone in line because
together they'll make 37 dishes for
lunch in just 3 hours.
>> Nobody want to come in a restaurant with
cold food.
I want them running and as you can see,
they run.
They run.
>> On one end of the kitchen, cooks chop
all the fresh produce for the salad bar
and stewed vegetables.
>> [music]
>> Two people work the fryers, dropping in
okra and chicken.
Deborah's right behind them, singing out
instructions.
>> Now, shake it. Yep, let that basket do
the work. There you go. Voila.
>> [laughter]
>> Over in the bakery section, chefs whip
up cornbreads and pies piled high with
meringue.
This kitchen might look like a
well-oiled machine, but before opening
the Magnolia Room, Louis didn't have any
restaurant experience. He worked in
Macy's.
>> I don't know how to cook. I mean, I
don't like cooking, I don't you know, I
don't enjoy it.
>> But when he noticed that a nearby S&S
was selling its old equipment at a
discount, he got into the restaurant
business. [music]
>> It was a fire sale. I got all the
equipment uh for $24,000,
so it was a steal.
>> [music]
>> To duplicate it today would be about
$200,000.
>> And it was a huge gamble.
>> Foolish looking back on it, I
didn't realize how horribly complex
restaurants were. So,
>> [music]
>> the journey all along, at least in the
early days, was should I keep doing this
or not, you know, should I just fold?
>> He chose a shuttered dinner theater as
the site of his new restaurant because
of its size.
>> It was hard to find a building that
could accommodate a stainless steel
50-ft serving line.
>> [music]
>> It is two 25-ft long sections, and the
poor thing arrived and it was just
sitting on its side, like two sections
of a beach whale. It broke my heart, but
now look at [music] it.
It's back alive.
>> Since Louis didn't know how to run a
cafeteria, he hired people who did.
>> It's just an entirely different way of
[music] of feeding the customer and
serving the customer, and you need
people that have had that experience.
>> He convinced Deborah to leave her post
at an S&S in Baton Rouge, Louisiana,
where she says the food quality had
dipped.
>> They changed so much. They got [music]
away from the old traditions, though.
Nobody didn't want that.
Less guests coming in.
Less hours.
>> Lewis found server Sherrell Summers at
another S&S in Atlanta. And waitress
Tenisha Williams from a Piccadilly in
Atlanta, where she worked for 23 years.
You're going to get my tray? It's pretty
heavy, though.
>> Oh, I know.
I can handle it.
>> Look at her.
Doesn't even flinch.
>> No.
>> Thank you.
>> Not at all.
>> Yeah, this a happy place to be. You know
I love it here.
>> Yeah, I can tell.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> [laughter]
>> Some of Lewis's chefs even brought old
recipes from former chains, but upgraded
them with fresh ingredients. Like the
pies got real vanilla instead of
artificial, and butter in place of
margarine.
That's partly why Lewis moved away from
the old cheaper cafeteria model and
started charging more.
His main dishes on average are 28% more
expensive than those at Matthews.
Despite the cost, the Magnolia Room has
thrived, Lewis says, [music] because it
went back to what made the chain so
successful in the first place.
Really yummy food.
>> All of these cafeterias used to have
exceptionally [music]
good food on the level of what we're
serving here. But they abandoned it. But
I will always raise the price before I
cut the quality.
>> And he says people are willing to pay.
[music]
How often do you come in here?
>> Six to seven times a week.
And well, with the price of groceries, I
don't see much cost difference.
>> The Magnolia Room's customers aren't the
only ones doing the math.
>> When prices rise, people want to feel
like going out to eat is worth it.
>> In 2025, US fast food prices climbed
faster than casual sit-down restaurants.
>> In a K-shaped economy, lower-income
consumers are pulling back on spending,
not eating out as much, and
higher-income consumers are still going
out, but if they're realizing that
they're spending 12 to $15 at the
drive-thru, they're [music] starting to
think, I could just go someplace and sit
down and have a better experience for
the same amount of money.
The brands that are offering bigger
portions at reasonable prices like Olive
Garden, Texas Roadhouse, Chili's,
they're seeing traffic growth. But
traditional fast food giants like
Wendy's and McDonald's just aren't
seeing the same momentum. And that shift
is happening across the industry, not
just at casual chains.
>> For the Magnolia Room, that shift is
showing up at the register.
>> They do all the work. All I have to do
is enjoy it.
Nothing in here is canned.
Nothing saw the inside of a freezer.
>> Most of the comments we get are that
it's an excellent value because [music]
it really is the same level of freshness
and quality that a fine dining
restaurant would order.
>> Just like the cafeterias of the '50s,
Lewis's Kitchen makes everything from
scratch.
>> People can't believe we still do that.
We run a very good food cost. We run a
good labor cost and everybody's happy.
So, this notion that it can't be done in
today's world because of the high
expense of [music] labor is not what I
found.
>> But were Lewis's claims of quality
legit? I put them to the test. First
with the fried chicken.
>> That is some crispy skin.
Mhm.
I don't understand how they fried that a
few hours ago yet it's still so crispy
and so juicy.
>> That chicken was an absolute standout.
>> And look at the size of this piece. I
mean, that's a whole chicken.
It's the size of my head.
We got the chicken pot pie with the
biscuit on top.
That's a power move. Instead of
dumplings, putting a giant biscuit on on
Look at that crab stuffed catfish. Ooh.
Woah. You get hit with those like really
strong Creole spices at the front and
then that briny note in the back. Off a
cafeteria line. Are you kidding me?
I'm going to try fried okra.
Mhm.
The only thing Matthews might have won
on was the mac and cheese. It doesn't
really have the the cream sauce that we
saw at Matthews. This is more like
soufflé almost.
Considering how much butter we saw go on
top, it's kind of silly I'm putting more
on, but you know, when in the South.
That's that melt-in-your-mouth
pillowiness.
Oh, it's so yummy.
And these sweet potato balls were a
surprise home run. Marshmallow sweet
potato, saltines fried together in a
bunch of sugar.
Mhm.
I don't think I've ever tasted anything
like that. That feels special.
So, the Magnolia Room's food was
delicious.
But it also reimagined what a cafeteria
could [music] be and rebuilt a community
around its food. One that I was
immediately scooped up into.
>> [music]
>> This is just like that you would cook it
at home.
>> Yeah. Yeah. But you don't have to cook
it. You just come here and let them cook
it.
>> here.
>> I met this couple, Mama Eula and her
husband Mr. Maddox, in line and they
invited me to sit with them.
>> You're old and antique.
>> I doubt it.
>> 78 and 75.
>> I'm telling you.
>> with the program? What's wrong with you?
>> I'm telling you, Southern food makes
everyone look young, I think.
>> [laughter]
>> You want any gravy on your dressing?
>> When you come in here, [music] it's warm
and it's welcome.
>> Yeah.
>> It's like a family. It just feel like
home.
>> Yeah.
>> It really feels like [music] home. You
know what I mean, you, Matt?
>> Yeah.
>> Just like we've been knowing each other
what? How long?
>> [laughter]
>> I've known you my whole life, actually.
>> I'm from the country. This is just like
some food that you would take off the
stove, put on your table, and your
family would eat.
>> That's what this restaurant is all
about.
>> This is the caring place. And you can be
my daughter, too, and you can be my son,
too.
>> I'd be honored. Thank you.
Waitresses hugged the folks who stopped
in and knew their names and orders by
heart.
>> It is wealthy people.
>> [music]
>> It is low-income people. It is all
racial groups.
It is old, and [music] it is young. I
think this food is a great equalizer.
>> I wondered if Lewis could rescue other
failing cafeteria chain locations.
>> There's a few K&W's that I've seen empty
at this time.
>> I I'm just salivating. [music]
It's just driving me crazy. I'm like,
these would be so successful as a
Magnolia Room. Yeah, so
you never know.
But if this is the only one, this is the
only one. [music] It does sort of make
it special.
>> Michael doesn't have plans to duplicate
[music] Matthew's Cafeteria, either.
He's focusing on the community that's
already there, relying largely on
hospitality manager Candace Caswell
[music] to make people feel at home.
I caught Candace making little table
bouquets with holly from her yard.
[music]
>> A lot of our customers
have been coming here forever, and some
of them are alone.
>> Yeah.
>> You know.
And they don't have anybody, [music] so
it just kind of makes for a homeier
atmosphere.
>> That's really sweet for you to even
think about that.
>> Aw, well, I love people, and uh
you know I have a gift [music] of gab,
Abby.
>> [laughter]
>> Matthew's frozen in time [music] has
long known that it needs to be ready to
serve whoever it shows up hungry.
>> [music]
>> You know, everything seems in [music]
popular culture to come full circle.
Bell-bottoms become cool again, haircuts
become cool again, and then
luckily for [music] us, I think we've
hung around long enough
to where
maybe the way we used to do things
[music] is cool again.
>> Magnolia Room and Matthews have held
onto something the rest of the
restaurant [music] industry is clamoring
for.
The idea that a meal can still be
communal.
And for the people who keep coming back,
>> [music]
>> that's worth standing in line for.
>> Don't give up on us. Don't give up on
us. If you're ever within range of
[music] Tucker, Georgia, and you want to
see the way it used to be done in the
South, and it's still being done right.
>> There are nannies, and then there are
Norland Nannies who are trained to give
the best care under even the most
extreme conditions.
>> Imagine if Mary Poppins
fought off attackers.
Or pulled a car out of a skid.
These are just two of the skills taught
at the UK's prestigious [music] Norland
College, which has been training elite
nannies for over a century.
But hiring a Norland nanny can cost
nearly $200,000 a year.
Some of their ultra-rich clients include
Mick Jagger and the British royal
family.
>> We always [music] get the jokes about
what James Bond meeting Mary Poppins.
It's not about that at all. We're not
trying to turn them into bodyguards.
>> But keeping up with global demand,
especially from the US, has been hard.
>> We know, for example, in New York alone,
uh we had nearly 100 jobs in the past
few years, uh but we weren't able to
fulfill those jobs.
>> To help address that need, the class of
will graduate nannies from the US for
the first time.
But each year Norland accepts only about
100 new students into its four-year
program, which makes nabbing one of
these highly skilled nannies quite rare.
So, what does it take to be a Norland
nanny?
And is hiring one worth the cost?
>> Wind the bobbin up. Pull. Pull. Pull.
Oh, the chaos has begun.
The chaos has begun.
>> Meet Roxanne, a second-year student from
New Orleans.
>> Abraca
dabra.
>> She's in a temporary chaperoned
placement with these triplets for 6
weeks.
This is the first time Norland has
allowed the filming of one of its
students on a placement.
The parents asked that we hide the
babies' identities. [music]
Roxanne started nannying as a side gig
to pay her way through university, where
she pursued a degree in American studies
and English.
>> Oh my goodness.
>> I just realized this is what I want to
do.
Uh but then obviously there was talk
about that not being a career. It's
always been go into STEM, [music] you
know, engineering. Do you want to be a
doctor? Do you want to be an architect?
And that's when I just kept pursuing my
studies in hopes to make a career. And
then when I finished my studies, I went
straight [music] back to nannying.
>> One misconception families often have is
that nannies are just glorified
babysitters.
But peek inside any class at Norland and
you'll see a break from that stereotype.
>> We're trying to raise that awareness,
give them that that sort of additional
insight and perspective that will help
to ensure that they can maximize the
care and safety of the children that
they look after.
>> Although Norland is respected and
well-known here in the UK, third-year
student Emma from Salt Lake City
struggled to explain the school to her
family.
>> They're like, "What is this? What What
do you mean you're going to go abroad to
be a nanny? That's not You're never
going to make money."
>> In the US, nanny salaries vary widely,
but ZipRecruiter reports an annual
average of about $49,000.
Meanwhile, the average salary of a
Norlander who works overseas is a little
over $101,000.
>> Strike.
>> That's a price some families are happy
to pay for their child's care and
safety.
>> It's just giving them the basic
foundations to defend themselves while
still keeping the
the children safe.
>> Keep it very, very simple. And the
simpler it is,
the easier it is to protect your charge.
I'm right-handed,
so I'm keeping my right hand free. I'm
protecting my charge. Okay? The attacker
comes forward and goes to a strike. Go.
One.
I can still put my hand up to defend,
but I'm keeping my arm up in a defensive
manner.
>> I feel like I've really been able to
learn what to do in an emergency and be
able to kind of know what to look out
for.
>> Hopefully, you don't have to use this,
>> Unfortunately, I have had an experience
where a man tried to take the little
girl that I used to look after. I said,
"You need to give her back." And he
said, "No." And so I just I just had to
pull her off of him while holding onto
the buggy where her baby brother was.
It is scary, but that's why I think
parents hire Norlanders because we are
given that extensive training for these
worst-case scenarios.
>> Worst-case scenarios like having to
control a car while dealing with poor
weather conditions and slippery roads.
Students learn advanced driving
maneuvers in their third year.
The program also includes 3 years of
specialized training and a fourth year
of paid employment as a probationary
nanny.
The training builds on itself over time.
Take cooking, for example.
In year one, students learn the basics.
Year two challenges them to prepare
meals for different dietary needs.
And year three has them learn advanced
baking skills. [music]
The students will even spend 28 hours on
a module called fabric friend.
>> We were making a fabric friend to help a
child through transitions.
Um, so that might be going to school.
Um, it could be going to bed at night.
It could be dealing with their emotions.
>> Nice way to be creative.
>> An entire class dedicated to making a
toy might seem excessive, but students
also learn the basics of sewing and
mending.
>> Sewing used to be viewed as quite
old-fashioned, but [music] in the in
today's world of trying to protect our
future and sustainability, it's now back
in vogue. That whole idea [music] of
repair and recycle and so on.
>> Practical skills make up about a third
of the curriculum. First-year student
Frankie, from Charlotte, North Carolina,
is starting from square one.
>> Not having worked as a child care
professional, it's been really nice to
have the, you know, practice with the
basic care skills, holding a baby.
>> Diaper changing is part of the basic
care skills module that all first-year
students must complete along with
hygiene, first aid, and car seat
installation.
>> So, always think overlap
overlap.
So, what normally go over your lap goes
over the child's lap.
>> Is that green?
It's green.
I did it.
>> Yay!
>> I was worried that the course was going
to be
too difficult for me, [music] that I
wasn't going to fit in.
But, I realized very quickly that
everyone who comes [music] here is the
kind of person who would thrive here.
It's such a British institution. It's
got such history and heritage behind it,
and that's a big It was a big draw for
me.
>> The college guarantees paid employment
for all its graduates.
Norland runs its own employment agency
that collects a one-time placement fee
from families.
>> The funding that we receive from the
income generated from the agency is used
to bursary provision. So, we have a very
strong commitment to widening
participation, [music] not least because
we want to change our student
demographic to reflect the wider
society, but also because we know that
the finances can be a big barrier.
[music]
>> It was going to be an investment, but
Norland does offer scholarships, so that
made it possible for me to come as a
student.
>> Norland's tuition is a little more than
$27,000 a year for international
students, almost $4,000 more than it
costs UK students.
All in, that's close to the average
annual cost of out-of-state college
tuition in the US. And, it's close to
the middle of the range that
international students pay for the
average public bachelor's program in the
UK.
One unique expense is the near $1,300
every student shells out for the classic
Norland uniform.
The promise of a high salary directly
out of college draws students to apply
despite the costs.
>> Within five years of graduating, our
students who have invested less money
than perhaps a doctor might have done,
are already earning higher than a
doctor's salary.
>> Fresh out of medical school, doctors in
the UK can expect a basic salary of
about 52 to 59,000 dollars. Meanwhile,
Norlanders can earn almost 75,000
dollars right after graduation. And
after a decade of experience, salaries
for overseas placements can exceed
170,000
dollars, the school says.
>> When I looked at the curriculum, it was
exactly up my alley. That's why I think
Norland [music] is so transformative
because they've taken this concept of
what used to be the help and turned it
into an expertise.
>> Norland's reputation is well over a
hundred years in the making.
>> It's lovely to see how some of the core
values and core traditions have
remained, but not necessarily [music]
everything.
>> The school was established in 1892 by
infant teacher Emily Ward.
>> She created [music]
the world's first child care training
institute in essence because she saw all
the way back in the Victorian times how
important it was to have adults who were
supporting young children.
>> These black books contain an account of
every student who studied at Norland.
>> In 1892, there wouldn't be any male
names here, but now we have male names,
non-binary names entered into our books
today. We're working very hard to try
and challenge the stereotype around
[music]
the Norland nanny.
>> Even the uniform, which some consider
old-fashioned, has evolved.
>> This is a cohort from 1923. [music]
This is her uniform. We have updated it
a little bit. You don't have to wear
corsets anymore, of course. We've made a
gender-neutral uniform as well. [music]
We've retained it because partly because
our students really want to wear it. But
we also think it's very important
[music] from a symbolic point of view,
as well as in terms of helping them to
develop their [music] professional
identity.
>> The uniform is a symbol of the Norland
ethos. Honor its history, but adapt to
the times.
>> And of course since then we've learned
so much more about
early years development. We now know
[music] that 80 to 90% of brain growth
seems to take place more or less in the
first few years of life.
Ooh.
There we go.
>> New insights yield new training methods.
This is Emily.
>> Come on, Emily.
>> A virtual baby named after the founder,
who likely couldn't imagine technology
like this would ever be part of her
school's curriculum. These robo babies
simulate the demands of infant care and
teach lessons that might save a real
baby from danger.
>> Um so, the sensor in the neck measures
whether you let the baby's head go. So,
for example, I wouldn't do this with a
[music] normal child, but if we were to
simulate a response from Emily.
>> [laughter]
>> This feels so wrong.
>> The robo baby is supposed to cry just
like a real one if it needs a diaper
change, is hungry, or is too hot. But,
occasionally there's a glitch.
>> She apparently has a very good neck.
>> [laughter]
>> We have made sure that over the last 130
years that our course remains
up-to-date, cutting edge, but we've also
retained some of those core values, some
of those core traditional skills and and
knowledge that children have always
needed.
>> While some of that knowledge is
universal, Norland recognizes that the
needs of an international family might
differ from those of a British one.
>> One of the other things that's changed
over the last past few years is that we
have acquired an international student
sponsor license.
>> After Brexit in 2020, Norland was
required to apply for a student visa
sponsor license to continue accepting EU
students. When the license was granted
in 2021, Norland started accepting other
international students as well.
>> We know that there are all sorts of
different families out there with
different needs, [music] different
context, different cultural context, and
so on.
>> Specifically, about 40% of advertised
international jobs for Norlanders are in
the United States.
>> We know that we have a large demand for
our graduates in America, but we're not
always [music] able to place them there.
If we have American students, of course
that's ideal.
>> Despite the global demand, Norland keeps
class sizes small.
>> We're not trying to be like the Beales
[music] and keep
>> [clears throat]
>> keep them rare deliberately. The only
reason we are so small is because of the
cost of the course.
We know that if we were able to roll
this out and have [music] a thousand
plus students a year, we certainly have
the interest, but it's it's not
necessarily sustainable in terms of the
intense training, the ratios.
>> More personalized instruction for the
nannies means more personalized care for
their charges.
Roxanne's placement with the triplets
will put everything she's learned to the
test.
>> You think, okay, do I have enough limbs
to do this? [music] And then you get
innovative.
Invention is ready.
>> To rein in the chaos, Roxanne uses a
child care principle called attunement.
>> So, really [music] being connected to
the child, really understanding their
needs not just from a basic level, but
an emotional level.
And [music] I think that has definitely
been what's
been so helpful in these challenging
[music] moments. And even just looking
them in the eyes can calm them
sometimes.
>> Good job. Well done, you.
>> You try to be organized, but then you
have a million trillion other jobs that
you literally have to do. And then
you're like, oh, this, and then I have
to do that. But you have to have that
spontaneity. [music] I'm equipped to be
able to advise people. I know what's
happening neurologically. I know
developmentally what's happening with
that child. And it's science. [music]
It is science. And I think that's where
it's something profound and [music]
actually I feel proud.
I'm like, yeah, you know, I'm going to
be a New Orleans nanny.
>> Most people who train to guard the Tomb
of the Unknown Soldier don't complete
the program, making it one of the most
coveted assignments in the US Army.
>> [music]
>> This is the Tomb of the Unknown Soldier,
guarded 24 [music] hours a day, 365 days
a year.
It's one of the most exclusive [music]
assignments in the Army
and one of the most difficult to attain.
19-year-old Private Joshua Beckman is
about to take the uniform inspection
test. It's one of five tests he must
pass to earn the coveted Tomb Guard
identification badge and officially
become a sentinel. Only 735
Tomb Guard badges have ever been
awarded, making it the second rarest
badge in the Army behind the Army
Astronaut badge.
The active sentinels inspect every
detail of Beckman's uniform using a
micrometer, measuring down to the 64th
of an inch.
Passing the test will move Private
Beckman one step closer to becoming a
Sentinel. If he fails, he could be
reassigned away from the tomb.
>> [music]
>> Every year about 4 million people visit
Arlington [music] National Cemetery near
Washington, D.C. Every day they pay
their respects at the Tomb of the
Unknown Soldier.
>> There is this [music] weird feeling that
you get when you get out there. You have
this feeling of bliss that's kind of
hard to describe. You know, only a
select few get to actually feel that.
>> [music]
>> The tomb honors unidentified American
service members who died in [music]
combat.
>> For in death, as in life, an American
needs no name to make him great.
>> Dedicated in 1921,
the tomb contains the unidentifiable
remains of three American soldiers
killed in combat during World War I,
World War II, and the Korean War.
>> Halt!
Halt!
>> Tomb guards watch the tomb in all
weather conditions,
extreme cold,
heat,
and rain.
>> Ladies and gentlemen, may I have your
attention, please?
I am Sergeant Johnston
of the 3rd Infantry Regiment, United
States Army.
Guard of Honor
Tomb of the Unknown Soldier.
The ceremony
>> Sergeant Kiley Johnston is the only
woman currently serving as a Sentinel at
the tomb, and one of only eight women to
ever earn the badge.
>> Present
arms!
>> What is that like?
>> Uh, it's an experience. I don't feel any
different uh any different than the guys
that are here uh and that do the job,
but it's a definitely realization when
people are like, "Wow, only eight." And
then I kind of take a step back and I'm
like, "Yeah, wow." I I don't realize
such an impact that [clears throat] I
have on like young women and stuff in
the military or just civilians that come
here and see, so.
>> Ready.
Halt.
>> Was it hard to get to that sentinel
role?
>> It was, yeah. It was very hard. There
was times I didn't think I would make it
or if I didn't have it in me, but yeah,
I definitely like pinch myself every day
that I'm here, so.
>> How does it feel that that's up there?
>> Amazing.
>> So, it's a huge honor to be a part of
this board. I mean, all the the other
soldiers that I've met throughout, you
know, throughout training, all the old
tomb tomb guards have come down and
talked to us about everything. It's It's
absolutely amazing. I can't wait to come
down in the future with my children and
and show them the board.
>> Before they become sentinels, soldiers
train for 6 to 9 months with a 90%
attrition rate. Those accepted are
allowed to guard the tomb on a temporary
basis while they train and test to
become sentinels. In the tests, tomb
guards are evaluated on their
performance guarding the tomb and
exhaustive amount of tomb knowledge.
>> When did the unknown receive the Purple
Heart?
>> 7 August 1976.
>> And their uniforms.
It all happens here
inside the tomb guard quarters
where Private Beckman is preparing for
his uniform test to be graded by
Sergeant Johnston.
>> So, seeing that, I just uh I know what
he's going through, so I do think about
that when I'm grading him, but I don't I
don't miss that feeling. I don't miss
the the nerves the nerves of the day.
They never go away. Never.
>> Tomb guards in training
start the day with a weapons strength
test simulating the ways they'll hold
the nearly 12-lb rifle while guarding
the tomb.
>> A lot of the reason we do the weapon
strength is because even if you go to
the gym all the time, it's it's awkward.
You could lift 100 lb in the gym and and
not be able to hold the rifle up
properly, sir. So, the the weapon
strength really does build that
endurance in the weird little small
muscles that keep the the rifle
centered.
>> Back when you tested tomorrow?
>> Yesterday.
>> Ah.
>> That kind of works out well then.
>> Yeah, they didn't see a test, so
>> Okay, so so you're going to be the star
of the the next Business Insider video.
>> And then he's going to fail on the test
tomorrow.
>> [laughter]
>> Sergeant Johnson will be the bad guy.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> We got to be perfect. I mean, standard
is perfection down here. Of course,
nothing can be tangibly perfect, but you
can get it as close as you can.
>> Back in the Tomb Guard quarters, it's
rare to see a guard doing anything
besides working on his or her uniform
and the components that go with it.
>> All arts and crafts down here.
>> Did you have much experience with
alterations and steaming?
>> I did not. I learned how to sew a blouse
here. I learned how to press a blouse
here.
Um
usually I had my mom do that stuff for
me.
>> What does your mom think about all your
new skills?
>> Uh she is happy that she doesn't have to
help me with uh
uh
ironing my clothes. I can kind of do it
on my own now, so.
>> I'm shining my shoes, so we have patent
leather shoes down here. We'll put coats
and coats of polish on our shoes um to
get it this nice finish that you see. It
takes a lot of practice to to learn cuz
when you come down here, you don't know
like you you might have some practices
of uh shining shoes with like a
microfiber and then just forget all of
that when you come down here.
>> At what stage are these shoes in terms
of where you want them to be?
>> they they need some work trying to get
them a little bit better to try to go
out later this afternoon. Every day that
you go outside, it it'll destroy the
polish. So, especially in the heat, the
the sun will cook the oils. So, you just
have to constantly keep up with your
shoes. I use Kiwi for my build coats and
then
Saphir black for for my shine coats.
Cheaters. These are here and you hear us
click our heels.
It's just two piece of metal screwed in
and then we have the same on the bottom,
too. So,
uh before before I'll go out I'll color
these with Sharpie so it's it's black
and on the bottom. We kind of roll on
the outside of our our foot. So, we got
that smooth walk.
And you should just be gliding across.
If you watch somebody's head while
they're walking across the plaza, it
should just be floating across in in a
straight line. That standard perfection
is always a few steps ahead of us and
we're constantly chasing that.
>> The Tomb Guards work in shifts, changing
every 30 minutes during warmer months
and every hour the rest of the year.
>> Bells, I'll see you out there.
>> In the Tomb Guard quarters, it's a
constant rotation of guards going out
and coming in.
>> That was money.
>> On the plaza, the Tomb Guard marches 21
steps down a black mat, stopping to face
east for 21 seconds. The guard then
marches 21 steps to the other end. 21
represents the significance of the 21
gun salute, a distinguished military
honor.
>> How hard is it hitting that exact spot
and making it 21 steps?
>> It's actually pretty hard. You don't
realize the big steps that you have to
take, especially if you're shorter. So,
we call hitting blocks outside. When
you're walking down the mat, it should
be what we call three blocks. So, the
single block, one step, the bigger
blocks, two steps. So, really striding
it out to hit those blocks outside.
>> Private Beckman isn't on the schedule
today.
He's about 12 hours away from his
uniform inspection test.
>> The color is not going to change. It's
just the chest that's going to change.
>> With more than 100 possible deficiencies
or gigs that can be counted against
them, it's one of the most difficult
tests the trainees must face.
>> I'm sure that'll be fine.
>> Testing criteria-wise, it's all
dependent on the grader. A grader could
say, "Oh, this looks good." Another
grader could say, "Oh, this looks like
crap. Like this sucks."
>> So, right here
I'd say it's it's fairly money. And then
you got to measure it from this side
right here, this edge.
You got to measure it
to the gold again. And I'm getting
15 ticks. Yeah, I've had this checked
like six times by this like six
different sentinels. So, this is
hoping this is going to be right on the
money.
>> Cuz the standard is perfection.
>> Yes, sir. All the time. Noth- nothing
nothing but perfection. And then
anything less than is is
you can't have it. Any trainee who
doesn't meet the standard or doesn't
actively try to meet the standard
kick him to the curb.
>> Sentinels in training are held to high
standards, but even more so are the
sentinels themselves. The Tomb Guard
badge can be revoked, which happens if
it's determined a sentinel has
dishonored the badge with their conduct
during or after their army service,
which can occur after a criminal
conviction.
>> Is the weapon ever loaded in the context
of guarding the tomb?
>> I can't disclose that, sir.
That's something that we we like to keep
under wraps
just for I don't know, the security
purposes behind it cuz we don't want
anyone thinking that they can come on
the plaza and do whatever they want cuz
they cannot. We will not let them.
>> Yeah, I have to. These are too big for
me, so.
>> Tomb Guards wear sunglasses, but not
just to protect their eyes.
>> We have the sunglasses so we we can look
around with our eyes as well, even
though our head is is straight forward.
So, I'm looking around with my eyes at
that time, just making sure that I I
don't see anybody looking like they want
to jump the chains and rails or no one
no one's being loud or disturbing the
peace.
>> [music]
>> Our cameras did not capture any
incidents, but many clips online like
this one show tomb guards admonishing
visitors who break the rules.
>> Remain behind the chains and rails.
>> Why did you join the army?
>> When I was When I was a baby, it's
probably not a great parenting advice,
but when I was a baby my dad used to
watch Band of Brothers while he was
feeding me. So, I grew up with
the 101st Airborne and I was looking at
those guys and I was like, man, that's
cool. I was first day of in-processing
into our battalion, they let us know
like, hey,
the two platoon sergeants going to come
up here and he's going to ask if anyone
here is interested. I was the only one
who raised my hand. And he brought me
down and showed me quarters. Here's
Private Beckman, he's 6'3", and the
assistant sergeant of the guard was
like, yeah, that sounds good, we'll
we'll we'll take him.
>> Like the 6'3" Beckman, most of the tomb
guards we encountered are also tall, and
that's by design.
>> Is there a height requirement?
>> Uh there is a height requirement, sir.
It's 5'10" for males and then 5'9" for
females. It gives a good image uh for
the US Army, it shows that we have fit
and disciplined soldiers.
>> Do you guys have like a signal or tomb
guard basketball team?
>> Uh we don't, but we should we should
probably get on that.
>> The next morning, it's time for
Beckman's uniform test.
>> Got some sleep last night, which was
nice.
>> How much?
>> Probably not enough.
>> [music]
>> You'll get your entire ensemble of
uniform items. You have to put it all
together in a way that keeps its
integrity. You have to just stand there
for however long, just having the
sentinels judge every little thing on
your uniform, and they will find every
little thing. Like, I thought I was
getting a little deduct, no. No, these
people are nuts.
>> What is that?
>> This sir?
>> Yeah.
>> This is our fat man's belt. Uh, we don't
wear traditional belts. We wear this to
in place of belt and provide back
support.
>> Now, I'm going to be here for the next
hour.
No moving.
Did you have coffee or anything?
I wish.
>> All right, tell me if it starts burning
your arm.
>> No, I'm going to need to flatten out.
Pain's only in my
>> Cringe.
>> All right, Beckman, you're going to be
taking your front test for test two.
>> Are you ready?
>> Sure.
Is it okay?
I feel like
>> Yeah, you're going to pass out or
anything.
>> I probably [snorts] will all right.
>> So, you
>> The inspection is scheduled to last
about 40 minutes.
The sentinels take note of any perceived
deficiencies [music]
or gigs that might be counted against
him.
At about the 35-minute mark, Beckman
appears to feel faint.
>> It's all it's getting all fuzzy.
>> [music]
>> Like when your vision gets all cloudy?
It was getting that. It was like if I
don't take a seat, I'm going to I'm
going to drop. And then I'd face plant
into a table. And that would not be
very Tomb Guard of me.
>> We're talking amongst like the sentinels
wondering if we should finish this test
um due to him not being able to stand
that long. So, that's another
requirement is that he should be able to
to meet that stand.
Um
So, yeah.
>> What happened?
>> Uh he just is feeling light-headed,
feeling a little dizzy.
>> That's a major give away. We're probably
going to cancel the test at this time.
And then he'll be able to test again at
a later date. But, I mean it's it's
probably unsafe for him to go out the
door later today and that's part of the
testing requirements. And then let alone
just he didn't stand I mean that's one
of the major things you have to stand at
attention for that time. So, he's he's a
major give away this time.
>> [music]
>> Uh all right, Magnus.
Unfortunately, we're not going to be
able to continue testing you. Not an
easy decision because we want you to
take test two, but with you feeling the
way you're feeling we can't send you out
the door confidently. And not being able
to finish the whole stand of the uniform
test. We know it's a long time, but you
know, it's it's just the way it is.
Everyone has to do it. Everyone has to
go through it. Um
>> If I were to
I I don't I don't know what that means.
Never mind. I don't know what it
>> You're good. I mean you'll be you'll be
taking test two again soon eventually.
Just relax. We're just looking out for
you.
>> Make sure you drink water.
>> Eat. Drink water.
>> [music]
>> Just go to straight back and change your
uniform.
>> How much time did he have left? To stand
at attention?
>> I'm not going to lie, he probably only
had probably not even five minutes. I
was almost done.
>> [music]
>> Hey.
Hey.
How you doing?
This is my fault.
I'll own it. Uh
I didn't I should have
taken more time for myself this four day
and and eaten
and done more to prepare my body not
just focus entirely on the uniform, but
uh uh
a failure happens. This place, failure
is very common. So, being able to being
able to
re-analyze it, come back in it next next
test with fresh sense of
of things I need to do is
it's going to be We're going to be good.
We're going to have We're going to have
a
good test.
So.
>> Sergeant told me that you only had about
uh 5 minutes left.
Uh is he uh standing at attention?
>> Definitely failing Failing sucks. It's
not something that anybody says they
like doing
or that they
enjoy, but
I'd rather
I'd rather fail at the beginning
and know what I failed at and then come
at it better than let's say I were to
get the entire way through the day, get
everything done, and then fail.
>> [music]
>> After failing the uniform inspection,
Beckman will not walk as a tomb guard
for the rest of the day.
>> [music]
>> Instead, performing duties like moving a
chain to allow the guards to enter
[music] and exit the plaza.
>> [music]
>> Very unfortunate, [music] but I guess it
will take it. We'll learn from it. We'll
get better. I'll get the gigs for my
uniform today.
And then we'll use that to make sure my
stuff's perfect next time.
>> [music]
>> 40 days later, Beckman got his second
chance. This time, he passed.
>> [music]
>> He's back on the plaza guarding the
tomb.
And his journey [music] toward
officially becoming a sentinel
continues.
>> Ultramarine blue is the most expensive
[music]
paint in the world.
Making it requires mastering the
techniques for extracting pigment from
lapis lazuli rock.
This is the most expensive blue paint in
the world.
It comes from these lapis lazuli rocks
extracted from mines in Afghanistan.
[music]
But you can't just crush up lapis lazuli
and turn it into paint like you would
with many other natural pigments.
It takes a laborious process [music] to
create the color called ultramarine
blue.
We found it priced as high as $460
for a 225 ml tube of oil paint. That was
on sale.
This identically sized tube of synthetic
ultramarine costs only $19.
Lapis lazuli pigment has been expensive
since ancient times, but modern-day
artists have the option of a much
cheaper alternative.
So, why do some still favor the natural
stuff? And why is it so expensive?
The first step in turning lapis lazuli
stone into paint is to crush it.
Next, keep crushing it.
>> Sometime I sneeze and it's [music] blue.
I mean, it's uh
uh my hair, uh they would be all blue.
>> Pigment maker Muhammad Irfan's goal is a
fine powder.
But not too fine, or else he will have a
difficult time extracting the bright
blue lazurite from the other minerals in
the stone.
If the lazurite isn't pure enough, you
end up with a muddy grayish color,
rather than the true blue ultramarine is
known for.
That's because the lapis lazuli rock
contains a mixture of minerals that left
in the mix [music] can dilute the color
of the finished product.
>> Can you see the blue blue parts?
So, it's all lazurite. It's lazurite,
pyrite, silicate. So, the our
job is to remove all those impurities
and just extract lazurite.
>> But isolating pigment isn't easy. When
Business Insider visited Muhammad's
workshop in Canada, he showed us the
Cennini method, named after the Italian
painter who most famously [music]
described it. It's one of the oldest and
most labor-intensive ways to turn lapis
lazuli into Fra Angelico, the purest
ultramarine blue pigment. [music]
It takes longer and produces less
pigment than other methods, so it's
usually reserved for specialty [music]
orders.
>> We extract lazurite by Cennini method
when we are supplying to different
museums and for the restoration
projects. [music]
>> What separates the Cennini method from
other methods is that the powder gets
turned into a dough.
Muhammad heats the lapis lazuli powder
with beeswax, [music] pine resin, mastic
gum, and linseed oil.
>> See like this one, mastic. So, when I'm
doing this, I I I sometimes
start eating them, you know, it's so
good.
>> Traditionally, the mixture is stored for
a week and kneaded every day.
Instead, Muhammad rolls his dough into
little balls and lets [music] them dry
for two or three days.
>> Wow, it smells so good.
This reminds me, you know, actually I
was raised in Pakistan, the north of
Pakistan, with pine trees.
All over you can see the pine trees, and
I can It feels me when I'm smelling this
one, it looks like
I'm in that area of my childhood where I
grown up. I used to make long sticks and
then extracted with hand, but I don't
use hands now. I have another machine.
>> This is an even bigger deviation from
Cennini's original method. He specified
that the pigment should be washed out of
the dough by hand, specifically the
hands of a young girl.
Mohammed's method is mostly hands-free,
opting for a ball mill that tumbles the
dough balls with steel balls [music] and
hot water.
>> They will push each other, and you know,
it will create a um
it will help to [music]
take out these lazurite. It will make
them soften, and so
the lazurite is going to
come quickly and easily.
>> After about 2 hours, the lazurite will
be pulled into the water, leaving the
other minerals stuck in the dough.
>> If I remove this
water,
you can see this.
This is all fine and delicate.
But, it need washing
five, six more times. [music]
>> After the final wash, Mohammed will run
the drained pigment through a
dehydrator.
And in about 2 hours, [music] it's ready
to use.
>> So, now you can see this is a beautiful
color,
and I'm really happy with the results.
>> It's not much.
>> See, with with the with the 400 g of
using lapis lazuli, we only got [music]
this much. And this is around
20 to 30 g.
This size of the jar of Fra Angelico
Cennini, it sells around $190.
>> Muhammad's company Demiro produces 4,000
to 5,000 lb of lapis lazuli pigment
every year, mostly using a secret
[music] method that he took 6 years to
develop.
While the Cennini method can take up to
4 [music] days to produce 1 kilo of
pigment, Muhammad's method yields up to
20 kilos in a single day.
>> That's for the bulk orders. Like Michael
Harding, he we supply to him, so his
orders are usually like 200 to 400 kilo.
So that we cannot extract by the Cennini
[music] method.
>> Muhammad has spent nearly his whole life
thinking about lapis lazuli.
He grew up in Pakistan on the border of
Afghanistan, the region where most of
the world's lapis lazuli comes from.
>> I think I was 7 or 8 years old and
someone brought lapis
>> [music]
>> rough to show to my grandfather. And at
that time when I saw lapis, I got so
fascinated with its [music]
pyrite and the color and I thought like,
"Oh, what is this?"
>> These days, you don't need funding from
the Pope to afford a version of
ultramarine blue. Artists can now use
[music] a cheaper synthetic option.
Today, it sometimes costs 24 times less
than the natural stuff. And while the
two varieties are mostly identical,
artists will still reach for the pricier
natural one for certain occasions.
>> Lapis lazuli has a crystalline
structure, so it reflects light. And the
synthetic one, it
absorbs more light. So that's when you
see the difference of
synthetic after painting. It's like the
lapis is going to be more brilliant,
more vivid than the
synthetic one.
>> Some artists like the textural quality a
natural pigment provides.
There's also simply the bottom line to
consider.
>> It adds value to their artwork. So, when
they're using synthetic, if some [music]
someone is selling a painting for let's
suppose $1,000.
But, when they use lapis lazuli pigment,
>> [music]
>> they can sell the same painting for
$5,000.
>> To turn the pigment into paint, Muhammad
mixes it with oil.
>> It's so smooth
>> [music]
>> that even I haven't used it. It mix so
well
if it's made properly.
You don't need to do the use the muller.
I use walnut oil um for when I'm
checking because it's not so yellow. So,
it's really [music] give me the real
it's shades and color and I can check
its quality.
For the last 10 years, the demand has
gone so up. Even individual artist and
[music] plus the companies. And
especially the last three, four years
because of the AI I see the big demand
for the real artwork now. So, our target
is to
make it available for everyone. So, they
can So, we can share the beauty of this
beautiful rock and pigment to with
everyone.
>> Lobsters are synonymous with Maine, but
lobster migration is adding a new
challenge to this hands-on industry.
Shelling a lobster claw takes quick
hands and a good knife.
Maine traps 90% of America's lobsters,
but 100 million pounds every year.
>> That one right there is going to look
real good on somebody's dinner plate.
>> But for decades, lobsters along the East
Coast have been shifting north as waters
get hotter.
>> 25 years ago this time of year, this bay
would have been full of boats and traps.
I'm the only boat hauling here today.
The population of lobsters up in here
has definitely changed.
>> That's a problem because many of the
fishermen here only catch lobsters.
>> I think there's always risk associated
with putting all of your eggs in one
basket.
>> For 7 months of the year, Stephen and
his brother Dan set sail in the dark to
pick up bait.
>> I'm 57. He's 55. But basically every
dollar I've made has come out of the
water right here since I was 12 years
old.
>> As they motor out to their first set of
traps, Dan preps that bait.
Just as dawn sets in, the work takes
off.
And it doesn't stop.
Stephen and Dan will empty over 300
lobster traps today.
Six traps are strung along one line or
trawl.
Color-coded buoys, like Steve's orange
and blue ones, mark either end.
A winch pulls in the line and Steve
hauls the 40-lb traps on board.
>> You get pinched pulling them out of the
traps. What hurts is when you slam your
elbow onto it and moving your arm out of
there.
>> The team throws back any bycatch or
species that aren't lobsters, like these
crabs.
>> We don't keep anything we can't sell.
>> They also toss back any lobsters that
are too big or too small to be legally
harvested.
>> It has to be at least 3 and 1/4 in from
the back of the eye to the back of the
shell. That's that's legal. That's big
enough.
If it's larger than 5 in it has to go
back.
>> If they come across a female with eggs,
like this one, that's also protected by
law and has to be thrown back.
They clip a V-shaped notch into the tail
to let other fishers know this lobster
had eggs.
>> But if you don't leave stuff in the
water for the future, you won't have a
fisher.
>> Dan fills the empty traps with bait.
Acadian redfish, menhaden, and pork fat.
>> What we're giving them is their junk
food. It's like walking by a donut shop
and smelling the donuts cooking so you
go in.
>> Then they push the first trap back into
the water to catch some more.
They have to be careful not to get
caught up in that line as it whips by.
That rope is one of the most dangerous
parts of lobstering.
It's why these guys carry a knife in
case the rope pulls them overboard, they
can cut themselves free.
>> He could fall off the stern in like 3
minutes before I realized he went
overboard and that's not like I was
ignoring him. It's just that I'm doing
other things.
>> Once the traps are safely back in the
water, Stephen and Dan slide rubber
bands around the claws of their latest
catch.
>> We try to bend the hard shells first
sometimes cuz they'll bite the other
ones.
I have to pay for everything except for
the bands. The dealer will give us the
bands.
>> Steve drops them into the tank below so
they'll stay kicking.
You want a lobster to stay alive all the
way until it's cooked so bacteria
doesn't grow.
Because they get paid by the lobster,
the team keeps a tally from each buoy
line.
>> Two.
Going to be a long day, Dan.
>> They want to catch at least 10 lobsters
from one trawl or about 2 lb a trap.
>> Anything under a pound is real bad.
Even when we're having a bad day and
we're not catching much, look where we
are. I'd much rather be here than stuck
in an office somewhere.
>> But for the last decade or so, rumors
have swirled that Maine's lobster
population could be at risk.
Scientists track the East Coast lobster
stock by the total weight of the
population, what's called the biomass.
>> If you were to pinpoint a location where
you could sort of balance that biomass
[music] on your fingertip, that would be
the center of gravity.
>> In the 1970s, lobster center of gravity
was actually right off Long Island, New
York.
Because of warming water, the population
collapsed there. The center shifted
north towards the stronger population
off southern New England.
But soon, the same thing happened there,
and that population collapsed.
By the late 2000s, the center had
shifted all the way to the Gulf of
Maine.
Fishermen here experienced a surge in
the lobster population.
By 2016, lobster landings had hit a
record high of 132 million pounds and
made up almost half of what was caught
in Maine.
Before this boom, fishermen here caught
everything from herring and mussels to
scallops.
>> Lobster became such a financially
productive activity during the boom of
our landings, and most fishermen focused
exclusively on lobster.
>> In the 2010s, going all in on lobster
seemed like a safe bet for fishermen.
They could earn more than any other
species, and lobster's price stayed high
despite soaring supply.
>> [music]
>> I think there's always risk associated
with putting all of your eggs in one
basket, and that's essentially the
situation we've created. [music]
>> But now the population is shifting
again, farther offshore.
Lobster eggs in warming waters inshore
aren't surviving at the rates that ones
in cooler waters are.
Because the Gulf of Maine is warming
faster than 99%
of the world's oceans, people have been
worried what happened in New York and
New England would happen here.
But scientist Kathy Mills says there's
still hope.
>> We have conservation measures in place
that are buffering some of the effects
of warming temperatures.
>> Measures like maximum size limits
introduced in the 1930s and V-notching
in the 1940s.
>> The conservation measure to protect
egg-bearing females is almost a century
old.
>> These have helped slow lobster's decline
off Maine. See how in the last few
decades the center of gravity hasn't
moved as far as it did in the 70s, 80s,
and 90s?
Not only does Steve throw back lady
lobsters, but his traps are also set up
so small ones can escape.
>> So the kitchen is where the food is. You
got two doorways in and then this is the
parlor back here
where they're all hanging out after they
eat.
Every trap has three, sometimes four
vents. These vents are designed to let
the lobsters out that aren't legal size.
>> While these catch limits in Maine have
helped, they probably won't stop the
population from shifting completely.
>> The population will not collapse. It
will decline, but to levels that we've
experienced in the past.
>> Like most scientists here, Cathy's team
predicts the center of gravity will keep
shifting north in the future. And as
lobsters move offshore, so too do the
lobstermen.
Small boats like Steve's that stay close
to the coastline are increasingly being
replaced with big ones that go
lobstering 30 miles out for days at a
time.
But big boats aren't investment most
young lobstermen can't afford. Even a
small rig like this takes a lot of money
to operate.
>> The traps and the buoys and the rope,
probably looking at about a hundred
sixty thousand dollars if everything was
brand new.
Am I worried about the the younger
generation? And I am because we've done
everything we can to keep a fishery for
them.
The stuff that we can't control, we
can't control.
>> Yeah, I'm in Bowdoin.
Yeah, Roger that. Just checking.
>> On small boats, lobstermen like Steve
and Dan will go out for just the morning
and pull into the Portland dock around
noon.
They sell their catch to Luke's Lobster
at $6.50 a pound for hard shell and
$5.50 for soft shell or ones that have
recently molted.
Ward Peck runs the tank room. His team
grades the lobsters based on weight and
quality as they come off the boats.
Ones with two full-grown claws get a
higher grade.
>> Uh so, you can tell this one lost this
claw. So, you wouldn't want to pay $50
for this on your plate.
>> They also sort them by the hardness of
their shells.
If you squeeze a soft shell, you can
feel water inside because there's still
room for the lobster to grow.
It also means there's less meat. Those
can only be sold to local markets before
they spoil.
A hard shell though?
>> It's like a bullet. There's no water in
here. The higher proportion of meat to
shell in a hard shell lobster.
>> Hard shell lobsters will fetch a bit
more because they survive longer and
they can be exported out of the state.
>> Here's something that you you would pay
good money for at a Manhattan
restaurant. Uh
the it has a crusher claw and has a
pincher claw. The crusher claw is
bigger. Pincher claw is more narrow.
3-lb lobster, I would not want to get my
finger in in their crusher claw, that's
for sure.
>> He's seen some pretty lobsters through
all his years of grading.
>> This guy's more of an albino and this
this guy is like the calico. He's albino
in spots. When they're this color, they
look prehistoric to me. Apparently, no
matter what color they are when they're
alive, once you boil them, they all turn
red.
>> From here, Ward will drop them off at
Luke's Lobster's restaurant next door or
send them to the company's processing
facility, about 20 minutes away.
Pablo Morales Rodriguez is working to
bring pulque, a traditional Mexican
alcoholic beverage, to a new audience.
This is the agave plant from Mexico.
It's used to make two of North America's
most popular spirits, tequila and
mezcal.
It's also the main ingredient in one of
Mexico's oldest fermented drinks,
pulque.
Pulque isn't nearly as popular as the
other two, but that wasn't always the
case.
In the late 1800s, pulque was Mexico's
most consumed alcoholic drink.
But because of false rumors, its
reputation as a drink for the poor, and
competition from the beer industry,
pulque almost completely disappeared.
>> [music]
>> Now, young Mexicans [music] are fueling
a renaissance of the dying drink.
But, can pulque become a global hit like
tequila and mezcal?
And how, against all odds, is it still
standing? [music]
Between tequila, pulque, and mezcal,
pulque [music] is the oldest, dating
back at least 2,000 years.
Even though all three drinks are made
from the agave plant, the way they are
made makes them taste [music] different.
Mezcal gets its smoky flavor from
roasting the heart, or the piña, of the
agave plant, while the tequila gets its
sweet fruitiness from steaming it.
Both liquors also have complex
distillation [music]
processes that can take weeks to
complete and result in spirits that
contain as much as 55% alcohol.
Pulque, on the other hand, is made
through natural [music] fermentation,
which gives it a slightly sour taste and
a much lower alcohol content, around 4%.
>> I haven't tasted anything quite like
pulque. Something like it's slimy, a
little bit thick, a little bit heavy on
the on the gut, but yet it's so tasty.
>> Pulque is also much simpler to make than
tequila or mezcal, but producing it
still requires the skilled hands of an
expert.
And Pablo Morales Rodriguez knows
exactly what to do.
He's been producing pulque in the town
of Omealco de Bonfil in central Mexico
for the last 8 years.
>> [music]
>> The secret lies in precisely when to cut
the agave, or maguey as it's locally
[music] known.
Pablo has to cut the plant at just the
right age to extract the best aguamiel,
[music]
the sweet sap the agave secretes that
ferments into pulque.
If he cuts the agave too early, it could
produce low-quality aguamiel. If he cuts
it too late, the agave might not produce
any sap.
Pablo uses a metal tool to scrape
[music] the heart of the agave.
>> The agave is typically left to rest for
anywhere from 3 months to a year to
secrete enough aguamiel to fill the
cavity.
But beating the bugs has made this more
[music] difficult for Pablo.
>> [music]
[music]
>> After 3 months, it's time to extract the
aguamiel from the agave.
Pablo places an empty bottle with a hose
into the cavity.
>> This technique has been used by pulque
producers, known as tlachiqueros, for
centuries.
Traditionally, they would use a hollow
gourd called an acocote [music] for this
step.
But Pablo says using an empty bottle is
more convenient.
Once the cavity is empty, he scrapes the
sides again to stimulate more aguamiel
production.
At this stage, the average agave plant
can produce anywhere from 4 to 6 L of
the sap a day.
Pablo collects it two to three times a
day. But unpredictable weather makes it
more difficult. If rain gets into the
cavity, it could spoil the aguamiel.
Despite the challenges, Pablo says his
family had no intention of leaving
[music] pulque behind. Even though
people stopped drinking pulque in
cities, it was still enjoyed in rural
areas like [music] where Pablo's family
is from.
It was small-scale producers like them
who kept pulque from disappearing
[music] completely.
>> [music]
>> They continued harvesting their agave
[music] plants and fermenting their
pulque in small rooms called tinacals,
like the one Pablo uses today.
He pours fresh aguamiel into a plastic
barrel with pulque [music] that's been
fermenting for up to 3 weeks.
>> [music]
>> He continues to add fresh aguamiel to
the plastic barrel little by little for
up to 10 days, depending on how strong
he [music] wants the batch.
In the past, Pablo's family made money
selling to local pulquerias, Mexican
taverns that specialize in serving the
ancient [music] drink. But these
specialty bars have been disappearing in
Mexico since the mid-1900s. [music]
In 1953, there were over 1,200
pulquerias in Mexico City. [music]
Nearly 60 years later, that number had
dropped to just 72.
Since the 1980s, there has been a
growing [music] effort to revive pulque
in Mexico.
In the 2010s, pulque started
experiencing a renaissance. Slowly,
young [music] Mexicans in search of ways
to connect to their roots began flocking
to the drink.
Indian farmers are finding a new market
to sell a fruit now trending in the
United States, even though it's been a
local favorite for a long time.
>> This is a mangosteen.
If you're unfamiliar with this tropical
fruit, that might soon change.
Because the demand for its flavor is
skyrocketing.
Just look at one of the 44.7
million TikTok posts with the hashtag
mangosteen fruit. [music]
In India, the largest producer of the
fruit in 2022,
a kilo of mangosteen costs $4.
But in the US, just one fruit can go for
$6.
Even the saplings the nursery grows from
the seeds of unsellable mangosteens are
flying off the shelves.
The global demand is so high [music]
that farmers in India are doing
everything they can to grow more,
including wiping their farms over the
produce to plant more mangosteen trees.
All for a fruit that couldn't be legally
imported into the US from Asia until
2007.
But stateside vendors told Business
Insider they've been finding ways to get
their hands on the fruit for decades.
So does demand go beyond TikTok-worthy
visuals?
And why is this purple fruit so
expensive?
Some describe mangosteen as sweet and
tangy
with notes of lychee, peach, and
strawberry.
Others can't quite figure out how to
describe it.
>> It's an emotion. If you eat, you will
understand. I can't explain the taste.
>> As global demand keeps rising,
mangosteen farmers in Asia are doing
everything they can to increase
production.
One way farmers are trying to meet that
[music] demand is by simply growing
more.
Merlin Woods Head Nursery in Kerala,
South India, decided to cut down its
other fruits in favor of mangosteens.
>> Right now we are cutting all coconuts
arecanut. We are only promoting this
mangosteen because we have profit
[music] in this that much demand we have
right now.
>> Mangosteens currently make up 50% of the
farm's profits. So Manu says it's the
right investment.
>> Future is fruitful. Hey, I feel like
that.
>> Other farmers like Shaju are catching
on, too.
Even the saplings the nursery grows
[music] from the seeds of unsellable
mangosteens are flying off the shelves.
>> This year, I have just one plant which
give me fruit for almost 10,000 rupees
worth fruit, about 40 kilo each fruit.
So I thought, why not? I'm taking 120.
I want to plant these saplings the best
possible way and I want to make it for a
commercial purpose.
>> He won't be able to capitalize on
mangosteens from those trees anytime
soon.
It takes up to 10 years for a mangosteen
tree to bear fruit.
They need a warm tropical climate with
high humidity and slightly acidic soil.
That's why they're mainly produced in
South [music] and Southeast Asia.
Once the fruit does grow, the farm tries
to ensure pickers don't [music] miss a
single ripe mangosteen.
Badu has been picking mangosteens at the
farm for 35 years.
During the peak season of June and July,
harvesters like Badu climb 40-ft trees
in hopes of finding the best mangosteens
considered first grade.
First grade mangosteens are 4 to 8 cm
[music] in diameter with a purple or
nearly black outer shell and a bright
white fleshy fruit [music] underneath.
It's a delicate dance as the climbers
race against the clock to pick
mangosteens
before they over-ripen or fall
ensuring no fruit goes to waste.
Pickers rotate through sections of the
grove quickly to control the quality of
their product and prevent mangosteens
from falling in between harvests.
And if one falls, it will quickly lose
its sought-after sweet and tangy taste
and become inedible.
>> This one is a fell down fruit. I think
fell down before 2 or 3 days [music]
because it's already
as a stone. We can't open it.
>> Even if a fruit on the ground isn't rock
hard, they still won't sell it.
Mangosteen can spoil within days of
harvesting,
>> [music]
>> so there's a chance it'll go bad before
reaching the customer.
But every mangosteen they do pick has a
predetermined destination, according to
Manu, whose father started the
mangosteen farm.
The destination guides harvesters in
choosing [music] which mangosteens to
pick.
Nearly a third of the harvest is
reserved [music] for direct customers
who come to the farm to buy their
mangosteen in smaller quantities.
The darkest, ripest mangosteens are sold
to them because they need to be eaten
immediately.
Another third is purchased wholesale by
other retailers. They pay 350 rupees a
kilogram or around $4.70.
These buyers seek less ripe, [music]
lighter purple mangosteens that can
withstand transport times.
The final third goes to middlemen,
including exporters who sell to other
countries.
The further Manu has to send the
mangosteens, the more expensive they
get.
Shipping the mangosteens by air is five
times as expensive as [music] ground
transportation, which factors into the
final price.
While only certain climates are suitable
for farming prolific mangosteen trees,
farmers can't depend on high yields
every year.
If a tree produces lots of fruit one
year, it will produce less the next,
causing production to vary in cycles.
Last year, Manu's family farm made 10
million rupees or about $119,000
in revenue from its harvest.
This year,
>> [music]
>> Manu expects a third of that.
He says, "Regardless of fluctuating
profits, his [music] family continues to
benefit from mangosteens' surprising
success."
But this growth is relatively new.
When Manu's father, Merlin Muthudon,
grew up eating mangosteens from a
[music] tree his grandfather planted
over 100 years ago.
It wasn't a viable business.
He didn't make [music] much money from
it initially.
But last year, his mangosteens [music]
sold for almost 18 times that amount.
Merlin started off with 80 mangosteen
trees, and now he and his sons look
after 1,000
and counting.
>> All the new generation peoples are not
into farming.
I have a message like you all go for
this kind [music] of farming.
And if you have a good marketing skill
also,
you can get a huge success from this.
>> Aneesh Malpani is dedicating his life to
recycling something particularly
challenging to reuse, chip [music] bags.
>> Humans make more than 6 million metric
tons of potato chips each year,
>> [music]
>> and most of them come in bags like this.
They're typically made of multiple micro
layers of plastics [music] and aluminum,
each serving a different purpose.
And they're engineered to keep snacks
fresh and crisp [music] for 6 months or
longer.
But this sophisticated design, used in
everything from yogurt pouches to juice
boxes,
>> [music]
>> has created a major environmental
problem since the material almost always
ends up in landfills.
>> It's considered, quote and quote,
impossible to recycle.
>> Anish Malpani quit his finance job and
dedicated his life to solving this
problem.
Since 2021, his startup has recycled
300,000 chip bags into sunglasses.
But why are these packages so difficult
to recycle?
And are big manufacturers doing anything
to fix the problem?
The middle of a modern chip bag is
usually made from plastic resistant to
oil, grease, and moisture.
But this doesn't fully block oxygen or
light, so it's often coated with
aluminum to form the innermost layer.
The bag's outer layers must be strong,
flexible, and printable. So, they're
made with two plastics.
The undercoat has the graphics, the
outermost layer protects them.
Before a bag is sealed, it's filled with
nitrogen gas to create a low-oxygen,
low-moisture atmosphere.
Together, this design helps chips
[music] stay fresh and crisp for 6
months.
And this deceptively simple-looking
design is everywhere.
In 2023, the world produced enough MLPs
to fill about 4 million garbage trucks.
And most recycling facilities don't have
the technology to separate or process
these packages.
So, they are usually sent to landfills
or incinerators.
>> MLP is the black sheep of the plastic
family. Nobody wants this material.
>> Without's headquarters is just one of a
handful of places in the world that can
recycle MLPs.
>> Because we were approaching this from a
problem-first perspective,
we chose the things that nobody wants to
work on. In the beginning, many people
thought we were idiots. Like, you know,
what are you doing? This is like doesn't
make any sense.
>> Anish and his team spent a lot of time
buying and modifying common
manufacturing machines like shredders
and extruders to recycle [music] these
packages.
>> It's not like all of them are designed
by us. All of them are off-the-shelf.
It's a combination. You know, it's like
a jigsaw puzzle, right? You kind of
finding the space and making it.
>> First up is a modified shredder.
It's equipped with a special vacuum that
pulls the lightweight films through so
it doesn't clog.
>> MLP which is packaging is very light.
So, it's very hard to [music]
sometimes shred them. You need like
extra force to to suck the materials so
that actually like get shredded
properly. In the first shredder, we
could do only about
1 kilo an hour maybe. Now, we do 10
kilos an hour.
>> [music]
>> Workers wash the flakes to remove any
glue or dirt.
>> [music]
>> Then they skim them
and transfer them to drying racks.
A technician weighs the dried flakes
before loading them into the company's
real innovation, a custom-built
100-liter reactor that reaches [music]
about 250°
and actually separates the layers.
It took 2 years to figure out the right
process.
Anish doesn't have a science background.
So, when he started Without, he placed
an ad online looking for someone to help
him build machines that recycle the
unrecyclable.
>> And I came looking for uh
scientist to help me tackle this.
>> That's how he found Dr. Jitendra
Samdani.
Jitendra's main challenge was to
discover how to separate the mix of
commonly used plastics that make MLPs.
>> That's why people don't go towards the
MLP recycling. It's not a simple kind of
waste.
>> He tried over a thousand experiments
until he figured out the right reaction
that would isolate three of the most
common types of plastics, polypropylene,
polyethylene, and PET.
>> That's the moment we say the wow moment
for us.
>> Jitendra built a reactor to standardize
and scale his new process.
It uses water with a high pH to cause a
reaction that partially separates the
layers.
The reaction dissolves the aluminum and
breaks the PET plastic into its basic
molecular structure.
>> And then what we get is a bunch of
building blocks.
>> Anish's current R&D lab can separate
about 8 kg of material a day,
but he wants to get closer to 100 kg
before he opens a larger plant.
>> And we're still [music] working on
improving the rate of the reaction
because we need to make sure that we can
do it in the most efficient way
possible.
>> The reaction leaves behind a mix of
plastics, some of which can't be used to
make Without Sunglasses.
Eventually, Anish wants to make bricks
with them, but for now they're just
stored on site.
To get the needed PET plastic, workers
wash the mix with sulfuric acid.
Then, they load the flakes into a barrel
full of water and connect two hoses to
something called a hydrocyclone.
It's typically found in agriculture, and
it uses centrifugal force to separate
sand and mud from water.
Here, that force separates the lighter
plastics like polypropylene and
polyethylene from the heavier plastics
like PVC and nylon.
The material is continuously run through
both the barrel and hydrocyclone for 45
minutes until the only thing left are
the lighter plastics, which get skimmed
off the top.
The plastics are dried overnight at 60°
C.
In the morning, workers remove the
flakes and run them through a machine
that compacts them into a more solid
form.
Workers then load it into a mixing
machine and sprinkle some of the
naturally green materials with a fine
black carbon-based powder.
>> Our material is not transparent. It's
either
green, gray, or black.
>> A technician pours the flakes into a
customized twin screw extruder that
mixes, melts, and pushes out the plastic
as a filament.
>> We don't add any virgin plastic, but we
do add additives and compatibilizers to
give it the energy and the life that it
requires.
>> These additives include widely used
chemicals which improve the plastic's
overall quality and durability.
The filament leaves the extruder at 200°
C and it's cooled rapidly with water
tanks.
Another machine cuts the filament into
pellets.
Recycled plastic often starts in pellet
form before it's shaped into a final
product.
And it took over 2 years for Anish to
figure out what his would be.
>> So, we brainstormed over 400 different
products. We shortlisted 70. Then, in
the 70, we looked at 27 different
parameters based on like team
excitement, [music] complexity, average
Amazon searches, and margins, and all of
that. And then, sunglasses scored very
highly on that.
>> The pellets are melted and injected into
molds for frames and hinges.
Anish estimates that a single pair of
glasses takes about five packets of
chips.
A robotic arm stamps the hinges with a
logo and a QR code so buyers know where
and when their frames were made.
Workers assemble each pair by
hand-cutting plastic lenses imported
from China and screwing [music] frames
together.
>> So, we can make between 500 to 1,000
sunglasses a a month.
>> All told, the company has recycled 1,500
kg of MLPs.
>> That's like close [music] to 300,000
packets of chips.
Um it sounds big, but it's not a lot.
We're this We're like a drop in the
ocean.
>> For now, Without only sells them online
in India for $10 a piece.
But, Anish hopes to expand the product
to the US, Europe, Australia, and New
Zealand.
>> The craftsmen at this factory don't make
just any instrument. [music]
They're assembling Selmer saxophones, a
brand played by greats like John
Coltrane.
>> The main body of a saxophone starts out
as a 0.6 to 0.7 mm thick sheet of
high-quality brass.
Thierry Oriaz has been president of
Henri Selmer Paris since [music] 2021.
He says the company sources all of its
raw metals from the same foundries in
France and Germany to maintain quality
control.
80% of the manufacturing process is done
by hand. And because of that, the Selmer
operation is massive.
The company has about 500 employees
making about 10,000 [music] saxophones
every year in its workshop. Each with
over 600 parts.
Each brass sheet is cut with a laser
cutter pre-programmed to get the most
[music] pieces from each sheet
with as little waste as possible.
These cutouts will form the four main
parts of a saxophone.
The neck, the body, the bow, and the
bell. Selmer makes six types of
saxophones. The four main pieces have
different specifications for each type.
After the pieces are cut and given a
basic shape, the bodies and necks are
bent by hand by a craftsperson called a
boilermaker.
The bow is also pushed through this ring
made in-house from liquid tin,
which gives it a more precise shape.
The flare of the bell is then attached
to a thin brass ring to reinforce it and
hammer it into place by hand.
The necks are bent into that crook shape
with this device.
Bows and bells are typically made by
pressing the sheet into a mold, creating
two identical halves, which are then
soldered together.
The workers pore over every inch of the
instrument, down to these mouthpieces or
beaks, which are molded from a
vulcanized rubber called ebonite.
Each one must be perfect.
Key parts of this production process
were invented by Selmer and were adopted
by the rest of the industry, giving the
company a reputation for quality that
goes back over a century. Take the way
the tone holes are formed. Oval circles
are first cut by machine into the body,
and raised areas known as chimneys are
pulled out using a method invented by
Selmer in 1922.
A machine grabs a circular piece of
metal inside the body and creates the
tiny ridge you can see here. And these
elevated chimneys help keep the
instrument airtight by providing secure
seating for the key pads. [music]
The sealing of a saxophone is crucial to
its final sound.
Selmer also pioneered a more recent
innovation, improving the keys on its
newest model.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The company spent 12 years designing the
Supreme, named after Coltrane's album,
working with dozens of saxophonists
around the world.
Selmer spent so much time on the keys
because it's the most important factor
in how the sax feels to the musician.
>> [music]
[music]
>> That's why quality control for the keys,
particularly during final assembly, is a
top priority.
Another way they test for quality is by
placing a small light inside the body.
This reveals any leaks or gaps that
might have formed around the tone holes,
which could affect the sound.
>> [music]
[music]
>> A saxophone goes through multiple stages
of polishing, both by machine and by
hand,
to bring out the luster
>> [music]
>> of the brass.
[music]
>> A special finish, while adding to
[music] the aesthetic, can affect the
instrument's tone and price. For
example, a tenor saxophone can reach
[music] about $30,000
with a gold-plated finish.
Selmer has also been engraving its
instruments with signature designs since
the beginning.
But the final step in making a
saxophone, and one of the most
important, is to check the sound.
And the best way to do this is by
playing it.
>> [music]
>> A play tester, like Matthieu Tomat, will
make sure everything feels and sounds
perfect by playing each assembled
saxophone.
Selmer requires its play-testers to be
high-level musicians like its customers.
Matthieu is currently studying for his
master's [music] at the Conservatoire de
Versailles.
If something sounds off, he will go back
and inform the final assembler, [music]
who will check for any leaks or flaws in
key assembly.
Once a saxophone passes the test, it's
packed up and shipped to customers
[music] around the world.
>> In Indonesia, there's a delicacy lurking
beneath these shallow muddy waters,
but it's in danger of disappearing.
This crab fisherman is looking for the
slightest movement on the [music]
surface of these muddy waters.
When a claw emerges, he sticks his bare
hands in to grab it before it grabs him.
Mud crabs like this one have large meaty
claws and are prized across Asia for
their sweet taste.
Here in Indonesia, villagers prepare it
with local mangrove fruits and a [music]
secret spice.
In Singapore, they're the centerpiece of
the national dish, even though local
crab populations have declined so
drastically that they're mostly imported
from other countries [music] now.
But mud crab habitats across Asia are
disappearing.
If Indonesia, one of the mud crabs' last
havens, [music] doesn't save the
mangroves where they live, the creatures
don't stand a chance.
>> [music]
>> The Indonesian government and so-called
crab villages like this one [music] say
they are replanting trees and cleaning
up pollution to help preserve the
species.
But is it too little, too late?
Kolik is a 51-year-old mud crab
fisherman at Kampung Kepiting Ekowisata
Bali in Indonesia.
He specializes in tracking down the
elusive creatures in their natural
habitats. Salt-tolerant trees and shrubs
known as mangroves that grow along
coastlines.
>> [clears throat]
>> Barrel-shaped bamboo traps called bubus
are an easy way to catch [music] them.
Kolik baits the bubus with fish or
chicken heads and drops them in spots
where the crabs usually feed [music] on
plants, mollusks, and crustaceans.
>> He also uses a bent iron tool to poke
around in the mud trying not to disturb
the delicate mangroves.
>> [music]
>> But catching mud crabs can be painful.
In 2020, the Indonesian government
outlawed harvesting crabs smaller than
12 cm
>> [music]
>> or weighing under 150 g. And pregnant
females are off-limits completely.
[music]
This crab village has its own slightly
stricter rules [music] to give the local
crab population in these swamps a better
chance to grow back.
Fishermen are only allowed to catch a
crab if it weighs at least 200 g.
But it needs to weigh 300 [music]
g or more to be sold and eaten.
So, smaller crabs like these will need
to spend about 4 months fattening up in
a plastic container they call a crab
apartment. Here the villagers can easily
feed them and monitor their growth until
they are ready to be eaten.
By focusing only on adult crabs, they
are allowing the younger crabs time to
grow large enough to reproduce and help
prevent population decline.
There are about 500 of these crab
apartments on site.
Made Sumasa is the head of the
fisherman's association Colic and other
local fishers belong to.
Once they weigh anywhere from 300 to 500
g, the crabs are ready to move out of
the apartments and into the kitchens of
the crab village's restaurant.
The local fisherman's association
founded the crab village and purchases
all of the crabs caught on site.
Fisherman here catch only enough to feed
the visitors of the restaurant.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Mhm.